<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Principles for yong princes Collected out of sundry authors, by George More, Esquire.</title>
            <author>More, George, Esquire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113368</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848604</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848604</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13712</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13712)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1689:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Principles for yong princes Collected out of sundry authors, by George More, Esquire.</title>
                  <author>More, George, Esquire.</author>
                  <author>More, George, Sir, 1553?-1632, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>George More = Sir George More?.</note>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel title page of STC 18068.5.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some leaves torn or cropped, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education of princes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13712:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRINCIPLES FOR YONG PRINCES. COLLECTED OVT OF SVNDRY AVTHOVRS, BY GRORGE MORE, Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Heare counſell, and receiue inſtruction, that thou mayſt be wiſe in the latter end.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London, 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13712:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13712:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable and courteous Reader, though I had no intention to publiſh this colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet now vpon ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for that alſo I hold it as fit for yong Noblemen and Gentlemen to read, as for yong Princes to vnderſtand, for that they may reap ſome profit thereby, I thought it not inconuenient to commit the ſame to the Preſſe, commending it to your good acceptance, and fauourable Cenſure, my meaning to you being of more value then my labour. And ſo I rest, denoted to doe you better ſeruice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEORGE MORE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:13712:3"/>
            <head>The Table of the Chapters contained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Regall and Politicke gouernment. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who fitteſt to gouerne. <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be iuſt in his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be true of his word. <hi>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be conſtant in his act. <hi>12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be ſecret. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be liberall. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince not to be couetous. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be learned. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be religious <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince not to ſhed innocent blood. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be circumſpect in giuing credit to reports.
<hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be mercifull. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince not to be proud. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be humble. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince not to exceede in anger. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be moderate in his dyet. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to be continent of life. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to beware of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites. <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who to be of a Princes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Not to commit the Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth to one Counſellour one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Not to place a Stranger in authority. <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dangerous to take ayde of a Stranger. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to get and keepe the loue of his Subiects.
<hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who to haue charge in war <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prince to bee well aduiſed before he begin Warre, and carefull in his fight. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13712:3"/>
            <head>PRINCIPLES for yong PRINCES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>The Regall and Politicke Gouernment:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in naturall things the Head being cut off, the reſt cannot be called a Body: no more can in Politicke things a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or Communality without a head be Incorporate. Whereupon the Philoſopher, 1
<hi>Politicorum</hi> ſaith, That whenſoeuer of many is made one, one amongſt them muſt gouerne, and the reſt be gouerned. Therefore a people deſiring to liue in ſociety together, and willing to erect either a Kingdome, or other Politicke Body, muſt of neceſsity chuſe one to gouerne that Body. Who in a Kingdome of <hi>Regendo,</hi> is called <hi>Rex.</hi> And ſo by the people is eſtabliſhed a Kingdome, which gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is abſolutely the beſt. And as the Head of the Phyſicall Body cannot change the veines and ſinewes thereof, nor deny the Members of their proper ſtrength and neceſſary nurriture: no more can a King (who is head of the Polliticke Body) alter or change the lawes of that body, or take from the people their goods or ſubſtance againſt their wils. For a King is choſen to mainetaine the Lawes of his Subiects, and to defend their bodies and goods. So <hi>Brute</hi> arriuing in this Iland with his <hi>Troians,</hi> erected here a Regall and Politicke <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13712:4"/>gouernment, which hath for the moſt part continued euer ſince, for though we haue had many changes, as firſt the <hi>Romans</hi> ſubduing the <hi>Brittaines,</hi> then the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> entring againe: then the <hi>Saxons,</hi> then the
<hi>Danes,</hi> then the <hi>Saxons</hi> againe, and laſtly the
<hi>Normans:</hi> yet in the time of all theſe Nations, and during their raignes, the Kingdome was for the moſt part gouerned in the ſame manner that it is now. <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſaith, that at firſt all that gouerned were called Tyrants, but afterward the good Gouernnours called Kings, and the euill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours Tyrants: for in the beginning, ſome men co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous of honour and glory, did by their ſtrength force the people to obey them, and to ſubiect themſelues to their lawes at their pleaſure, and ſo eſtabliſhed one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Regall gouernment, which done by force, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned againſt all right and reaſon by rigour, was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted tyrannicall. For though a man by force doe ſubdue Cities and Countries, yet he ought to rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon: and if he know God according to the Law of God. But when he is choſen, or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King by the people, and hath his power from them, he may not ſubiect the people to any other pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet he hath a great and large prerogatiue, which he may vſe at his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And here I thought not amiſſe to ſet downe ſome few Lawes and Cuſtomes of other Common-wealths, wherby their good gouernment and life may appeare, they not being Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ptolomeus,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> feaſting one day, ſeuen Ambaſſadours, at his requeſt, euery one of them ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto him three of their principall Lawes and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes. And firſt the Ambaſſadour of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaid, wee haue the Temples in great reuerence, we are very obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to our Gouernours: and we doe puniſh wicked men, and euill Liuers, ſeuerely. The <hi>Carthagenian</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour ſaid, in the Common-wealth of <hi>Carthage,</hi> the Nobility neuer ceaſe fighting, nor the Common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Artificers labouring, nor the Pphiloſophers <pb facs="tcp:13712:4"/>teaching. The <hi>Cicilian</hi> ſaid, In our Common-wealth, Iuſtice is exactly kept: Merchandize exerciſed with truth, and all men account themſelues equall. The <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> ſaid: at
<hi>Rhodes</hi> old men are honeſt: yong men ſhamefaſt: and women ſolitary, and of few words. The <hi>Athenians</hi> ſaid, In our Common-wealth, rich men are not ſuffered to be deuided in Factions: nor poore men to be idle, nor the Gouernours to be ignorant. The <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> ſaid, In <hi>Sparta</hi> enuy reigneth not, for all men are equall, nor couetouſneſſe, for all goods are common: nor ſloth, for all doe labour. In our Common-wealth, ſaid the Ambaſſadour of the <hi>Sicyonians,</hi> voyages are not permitted, becauſe they ſhould not bring home new Factions: Phyſitians are not ſuffered leſt they ſhould kill the ſound: nor Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, to take vpon them the defence of Cauſes and Sutes. And to theſe may be added, <hi>Anatharſis</hi> Letter to <hi>Creſſus,</hi> King of
<hi>Lydia,</hi> concerning the <hi>Gretians.</hi> Know (ſaith he) that in the ſtudies of <hi>Greece,</hi> we learne not to Command, but to obey: not to ſpeake much, much, but to keepe ſilence: not to be contentious, but to be humble, not to get much, but to content our ſelues with a little: not to reuenge our harmes, but to pardon iniuries: not to take from others, but to giue our owne: not to take care to be honoured, but to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be vertuous: Laſtly, we learne to deſpiſe that which others loue, and to loue that which others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, which is pouerty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>Who, fitteſt to gouerne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw to ſhew what manner of man is fitteſt to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, I reade in <hi>Liuie,</hi> that men borne in Armes, great in deeeds, and rude in eloquence, ought to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Conſuls: and that men of quicke ſpirits, ſharpe wits, learned in the Law, and eloquent, ſhould be for the City. For a Prince (ſo the Conſull was for his <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13712:5"/>time) ought to be a Martiall man, ſtout and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as well to defend his ſubiects, as to offend his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; great and worthy in his actions, as well to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his foes, as to be beloued of his friends: and not to be curious, to ſpeake eloquently, but to deliuer his mind plainely and wiſely: it being more neceſſary for a Prince to doe well, then to ſpeake well. For wiſe words are not commendable, if the deeds be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, whereupon the Philoſopher <hi>Pacuinus</hi> ſaith, thoſe are to be hated, who in their acts are fooles, and in their words Philoſophers. They that will therefore (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) haue glory in this life, and attaine to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after death, and be beloued of many, and feared of all, let them be vertuous in doing good works, and deceiue no man with vaine words. And he counſelleth the
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> to chuſe a Gouernour that is iuſt in his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, true of his word, conſtant in his act, ſecret and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall. Theſe be the principall morall vertues moſt ceceſſary in a Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>A Prince to be iuſt in his ſentence.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr a Prince ought to be iuſt in his ſentence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the words of <hi>Salomon, Sap.</hi> 1. ſaying, <hi>Loue Juſtice you that Iudge the Earth, For a iuſt King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. <hi>doth aduance his Countrey: and the King that iudgeth the poore rightly, his throne ſhall be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for euer.</hi> Therefore he ought not to be led, either by fauour, paſsion, or gaine: but according to equity and iuſtice: and to haue care that all his Counſellors and Magiſtrates doe the like. And to attaine to this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Iuſtice; a Prince muſt call to God for wiſedome, which he cannot obtaine, being of euill life. <hi>For wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will not enter into a ſoule poſſeſſed with malice, nor dwell in a body ſubiect to ſinne,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) Sap. 1. <hi>But if thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>call for wiſedome, and encline thine heart to Prudence: then ſhalt thou vnderſtand Iuſtice, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13712:5"/>and iudgement, and equity, and euery right way.</hi> Prou. 2. Therefore he prayeth, ſaying: <hi>Giue mee (O Lord) that wiſedome which aſsiſteth thy ſeate, and caſt me not off from the number of thy ſeruants, for that I am thy bond-ſlaue, and the ſonne of thy bond-woman, a weake man, and of ſhort life, vnable to vnderſtand aright, what is Iuſtice and Law: and whoſoeuer is the moſt perfect and excellent amongſt the ſonnes of men, he is to be accounted as no body, if thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth not aſſiſt him.</hi> Sap. 9. All good and worthy Princes haue laboured to attaine to this wiſedome, and to execute iuſtice moſt exactly, inſomuch that ſome haue not ſpared their owne children: ſo ſacred a thing they held Iuſtice to be. As for example, <hi>Brutus,</hi> who vnderſtanding that his two ſonnes were of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy for <hi>Tarquinus Superbus,</hi> cauſed them both to be put to death in his owne preſence.
<hi>Caſsius</hi> likewiſe ſeeking to get the loue of the people, and to make himſelfe King, was beaten to death by his father. <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanias,</hi> Generall of the <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> receiued 500 ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of gold to betray <hi>Sparta,</hi> but <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> his father vnderſtanding thereof purſued him into the Temple of <hi>Minerua</hi> (whither he fled for Sanctuary) and cauſed the doores of the Temple to be nayled vp, and ſo there made him dye of famine, then his mother tooke his corpes, and threw it to the dogs, not ſuffering it to be interred. <hi>Darius</hi> likewiſe, King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that his ſonne <hi>Ariobrazanes</hi> ment to betray him to <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> cut off his head. <hi>Titus Manli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> being challenged by one of the <hi>Latins,</hi> to fight the Combate ſtepped forth of his ranke, and in Combate killed him, yet becauſe it was done without licenſe, his owne father, being then Conſull and Generall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put him to death <hi>Poſthumius</hi> likewiſe, did the ſame to his ſonne. <hi>Fidericke,</hi> Earle of <hi>Harlebecque,</hi> and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſter of <hi>Flanders,</hi> hauing made very ſtraite Lawes, for the reducing of his Countrey to luſtice and good life, put his ſonne to death for breaking the Law, in taking <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13712:6"/>a basket of Apples from a poore woman, and not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them. <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, put his ſonne in priſon, Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> for breaking the Parkes of the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter. Henry</hi> the fourth, alſo commended the Lord chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>England,</hi> for committing the Prince to priſon, for tranſgreſsing the Law. And King <hi>Antiochus</hi> had that care to haue Iuſtice miniſtred, as he writ to all the Cities of his Kingdome, that they ſhould not execute any thing he commanded if it were contrary to Law: but they ſhould firſt aduertiſe him thereof: The Emperour
<hi>Juſtinian</hi> likewiſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Lawyers to be ſworne that they ſhould not plead in an euill and vniuſt cauſe. The like Law was made in the ninth Parliament of <hi>James</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that all Counſellours and Aduocates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they plead any temporall cauſe, ſhould take oath and ſweare that they thinke the cauſe to be good they plead. <hi>Lewis</hi> the ninth, King of <hi>France,</hi> was a iuſt and vertuous Prince, louing the good, and puniſhing the wicked, and was a Capitall enemy to ſutes, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Iudges to doe ſpeedy Iuſtice, ſo that ſutes then were laid away. <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> was ſo farre from being tranſported from Iuſtice, as when any made complaint to him of another, he ſlopped alwayes one eare, ſaying, he muſt keepe that for the party accuſed. The Emperour <hi>Adrian</hi> was of that integrity in Iuſtice, as one <hi>Alexander</hi> accuſed another before him, called <hi>Aper,</hi> and bringing his proofes onely in writing, he ſaid that his informations were but Paper and Inke, and perhaps forged, and that a man ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned but by honeſt and ſubſtantiall witneſſes, and therefore he ſent <hi>Aper</hi> to <hi>Rufus</hi> Gouernour of
<hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> (from whence he was brought) commanding him, diligently to examine the witneſſes againſt him, and to ſee that they were honeſt, and of good name. King <hi>Edgar</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had likewiſe that care to doe Iuſtice, as in Winter time he would ride vp and downe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13712:6"/>the Countrey, and make enquiry of the miſdemeanors of his Officers and Gouernours, and puniſh them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely that offended the Law. And as the followers of Iuſtice ſhall not onely be famous in this world, but ſhall perpetually liue, and receiue a kingdome of glory in the world to come, as ſaith <hi>Salomon, Sap.</hi> 5. So the Princes that miniſter iniuſtice, and do not iudge right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall reape infamy, and incurre the high diſpleaſure of Almighty God, as <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo witneſſeth, ſaying: <hi>Hearken (O Kings) and vnderſtand: learne you who are Judges of the bounds of the earth, in reſpect that power is giuen vnto you from aboue, and ſtrength from the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, who will examine your works, and ſearch your thoughts, and becauſe when you were Miniſters in his Kingdome, you did not iudge rightly, nor iudge rightly, nor keepe the Law of Iuſtice, nor walke in the way of God, he will appeare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you quickely, and horribly: for moſt rigorous iudgement is done vnto thoſe that gouerne. With the poore and meane man mercy is vſed: but mighty men ſhall ſuffer torments mightily, Sap.</hi> 6. And the royall Prophet ſaith, that God is terrible to the Kings of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75. Which doth very well appeare by the ſtrange puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he oftentimes inflicted vpon them, as vpon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who was drowned in the red Sea, purſuing
<hi>Moſes,</hi> and the ſeruants of God: vpon <hi>Nabuchadnezzer,</hi> who was caſt downe from his Throne, and made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to beaſts: vpon
<hi>Ozias,</hi> who was ſtrucken by God with a filthy leprie: vpon
<hi>Ioram</hi> by an incurable fluxe: vpon <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Tyrant, who rotted aliue: vpon <hi>Herod,</hi> who for killing Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the reſt of the Apoſtles was ſtrucken by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and conſumed with wormes whileſt he liued: vpon <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpricius</hi> King of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> who was deuoured with Woldes: vpon <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the Emperor, who was killed with thunder: vpon <hi>Seldred</hi> a <hi>Saxon,</hi> King of
<hi>England,</hi> who waskilled by the Dinel, as he was banquetting with his Nobility: vpon <hi>Drahomira</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13712:7"/>of
<hi>Bohemia,</hi> who for procuring the death of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuille</hi> her mother in law, a very vertuous woman, and of many Prieſts alſo, was, as ſhe paſſed in her Coach, ouer the place where the Prieſts were murthered, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp by the earth: vpon the wicked King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, Anno</hi>
1387 who fell into ſuch an infirmitie, that all his limbes were cold: for remedy whereof hee was ſowed in a cloath wet in <hi>aqua vitae:</hi> and when the man had done, for lacke of a knife to cut the thred in his needle, he burned it with the Candle he vſed, and ſo by chance ſet the cloath on fire, which could not bee quenched, but that the King lying three dayes in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremetorment, dyed thereof. And many moe for their iniuſtice and wickedneſſe, haue beene puniſhed very ſtrangely, and oftentimes loſt their Kingdomes: for a kingdome, as appeareth; <hi>Eccle. chap.</hi> 11. is transferred from Nations to Nations, for iniuſtice and iniuries. Therefore it behooueth a Prince to haue moſt ſpeciall care hereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>A Prince to be true of his word.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is requiſite that a Prince ſhould be true of his word, and faithfull of his promiſe, both towards God and man, for it is ſaid,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 23. <hi>When thou haſt made a promiſe or vow to thy Lord God, be not ſlacke to yeeld it, for he doth require it at thy hands.</hi> And
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. <hi>J deteſt a double tongue.</hi> And againe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 17. he ſaith, that <hi>a lying lippe doth not become a Prince. Cicero</hi> likewiſe <hi>De officijs,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>fides,</hi> which wee call fidelity, (conſiſting in the verity and conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of words promiſes, and couenants) is the foundation of Iuſtice, which preſerueth a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. One of the lawes of the Knights of the Band in <hi>Spaine</hi> was, that if any of them broke his promiſe, or falſified his word, he went alone by himſelfe, &amp; no body ſpoke to him, nor he to any. And the <hi>Romans</hi> had great care alwayes to performe their word; inſomuch, that <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13712:7"/>the firſt Temple builded in <hi>Rome,</hi> was dedicated to the goddeſſe <hi>Fidelity.</hi> And vpon a time, they wanting money to pay their Souldiers, and to maintaine their Armies, thought it better to ſpend the goods of the Common-wealth, then not to pay the Souldiers their wages: ſaying if the Common-wealth be not vpheld by faith and keeping of promiſe, it will not be vpheld by riches. And at another time, becauſe they could not ayde the <hi>Saguntines,</hi> according to promiſe in due time (they being beſieged and for want of ayde, ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Hanibal</hi>) did not onely build vp their City a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, but after this made warre in <hi>Spaine</hi> for reuenge, by the ſpace of 14 yeares. In which time they ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Turditanes,</hi> (who brought
<hi>Hanibal</hi> into <hi>Spaine</hi>) and made them pay tribute to the
<hi>Saguntines,</hi> and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of all <hi>Spaine,</hi> the
<hi>Carthagenians,</hi> and reſtored all the <hi>Saguntines</hi> that were either impriſoned or fled. <hi>Scipio</hi> making warre in <hi>Affrica</hi> againſt the <hi>Carthage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> granted them Truce for a time that they might ſend Ambaſſadours to <hi>Rome,</hi> to treate of Peace, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ambaſſadors returned from <hi>Rome, Aſdrubal</hi> ſpoyled 230 ſhippes of the <hi>Romans,</hi> whereupon <hi>Scipio</hi> ſent to
<hi>Carthage,</hi> to aduertiſe them of the breach of the Truce: but his Ambaſſadours could not be heard, but were threatned by the people. Soone after, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of <hi>Carthage,</hi> returning home from
<hi>Rome,</hi> came through the Campe of <hi>Scipio,</hi> who ſent for them, and told them, that though <hi>Carthage</hi> had broken the Truce and law of Armes, yet would not he breake the cuſtome of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which was to obſerue the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, and ſo let them paſſe. <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> likewiſe kept faith and promiſe alwayes with his enemies, though they broke with him. The Emperour <hi>Nerua,</hi> (ſucceeding
<hi>Domitian</hi> in the Empire, who had put to death diuers of the Senators) did promiſe that hee would put to death any Senator: which greatly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Senate. Soone after ſome of the Senators conſpired againſt him: which diſcouered, he would <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13712:8"/>not put them to death, becauſe of his promiſe.</p>
               <p>The Emperour <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> hauing made Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to giue 25000 crownes to him that ſhould take <hi>Crocotas,</hi> Captaine of the Theeues in <hi>Spaine,</hi> called <hi>Bandeleros: Crocotas</hi> offered himſelfe to the Emperour, and demaunded the money promiſed by him. The Emperour, for performance of his word, did not onely giue him the money, but his pardon alſo. <hi>Sextus Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyus,</hi> hauing warres with
<hi>Antonius</hi> the <hi>Triumuir,</hi> and meeting him vpon a treaty of Peace, and thereupon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiting of him to ſupper (giuing him his faith for his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance and ſafty) was moued by ſome to detaine him priſoner: but he anſwered, that to be the Emperour of the world, he would not falſifie his faith. <hi>Licurgus,</hi> brother to <hi>Poledectes,</hi> King of
<hi>Lacedaemonia,</hi> hauing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed fidelity to the King, refuſed the offer of the Queene, who being left great with child, offered to deſtroy it, and to make him King, if he would marry her. But he, like a faithfull brother, proclaimed her ſonne King ſo ſoone as he was borne, gouerning onely during his minority, choſen thereunto by the people. <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> brother to <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> being left Tutor to the Kings ſonne, was vrged by the three Eſtates of
<hi>Caſtile,</hi> to take the Crowne himſelfe, but he refuſed it, ſaying: He would neuer be falſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his brother dead, or his brother liuing, to whom hee had promiſed fidelity. And as theſe and many moe, are famous for their fidelity and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their word: ſo a number are infamous by their perfidiouſneſſe and breach of their word. For <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> cauſing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Indian</hi> Souldiers to be killed, (after they had yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelues to him vpon his word) ſpotted and ſtained the renowne of all his glorious Conqueſts, and royall vertues. <hi>Hanniball</hi> neuer kept his word nor faith with any, but to ſerue his owne turne. Therefore
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> (to whom he fled, vanquiſhed by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13712:8"/>
                  <hi>Scipio</hi>) made no account of him. And he going from thence to <hi>Pruſias.</hi> King of <hi>Bithynea,</hi> one as perfidious as himſelfe, for that he meant to haue deliuered him to <hi>Quintius,</hi> Generall of the <hi>Romans,</hi> whereof <hi>Hannibal</hi> vnderſtanding, poyſoned himſelfe. <hi>Siphax,</hi> King of <hi>Numidia,</hi> by breaking his word with <hi>Scipio,</hi> loſt his Kingdome and life in captiuity.
<hi>Ptolomeus,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> hauing promiſed ſafety to
<hi>Pompey</hi> (who fled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ouerthrowne by <hi>Caeſar</hi>) notwithſtanding put him to death, and ſent his head to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſee, and wept for ſorrow, and commanded them that brought it to be put to death. Shortly after, <hi>Caeſar</hi> aſsiſted
<hi>Cleopatra,</hi> killed <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> her brother, and made her Queene of <hi>Egypt. Alfonſas,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> King of
<hi>Naples,</hi> vnder the promiſe and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his father, got to come to him, foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Princes and Barons, who notwithſtanding his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, put them in priſon, and vpon the death of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (being foure and twenty yeares after) put them all to death. <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth, King of <hi>France,</hi> when he was Dolphin, made <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> beleeue that he would make a peace with him: whereupon they met at a place appointed, where <hi>Charles</hi> cauſed the Duke to be preſently killed. But <hi>Charles,</hi> after this, wearied with the warres, <hi>Phillip,</hi> ſonne to the Duke, made againſt him: and of the ſubiection <hi>England</hi> brought <hi>France</hi> into, by this opportunity, did recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile himſelfe to <hi>Phillip,</hi> and asked him forgiuneſſe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Ambaſſadours. <hi>Charles</hi> the laſt, Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> hauing giuen ſafe conduct to the Earle of Saint
<hi>Paul,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>France,</hi> tooke him priſoner, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered him to the <hi>French</hi> King, who put him to death. But
<hi>Sultan Soliman,</hi> the great Turke, did worthily pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his
<hi>Baſcha,</hi> for falſifying his word, who ſent into
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alona,</hi> to paſſe into <hi>Jtaly,</hi> landed at the Hauen of
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro,</hi> where the Inhabitants being aſtoniſhed, yeelded vnto him vpon his word and fidelity, that they ſhould <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13712:9"/>depart with bag and baggage: neuertheleſſe, he ſlew them all, except thoſe that were fit to ſerue for ſlaues. But he returning to
<hi>Conſtantinople, Sultan</hi> cauſed him to be ſtrangled for his diſloyalty and perfidiouſneſſe, and ſent backe all the priſoners with their goods into <hi>Italy.</hi> Thus you may ſee how honourable it is for one to keep their word, and what they deſerue that falſifie their faith: for a faithleſſe Prince is beloued of none, but hated of all, ſuſpected of his friends, not truſted of his enemies, and forſaken of all men in his greateſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>A Prince to be conſtant in his Act.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is likewiſe very fitting that a Prince ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in his Act. Firſt, to aduiſe well before hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, but after, reſolution to be conſtant, and not changeable: For Saint
<hi>Ambroſe,</hi> writing to <hi>Simplician,</hi> ſaith: that <hi>a foole is mooueable as the wind: but a wiſe man is not aſtoniſhed by feare, nor changed by force, nor ſunke by ſorrow, nor proud by proſperity.</hi> The
<hi>Romans</hi> beſieged <hi>Caſſelin, Fabius</hi> would haue giuen ouer the ſiege, but <hi>Marcellus</hi> perſwaded him to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: that as there are many things a good Captaine ought not to attempt, ſo ought he not to deſiſt or giue ouer an enterpriſe once begun and taken in hand.
<hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trand de Gueſclin,</hi> a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> ſeruing
<hi>Henry,</hi> againſt <hi>Peter,</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was by the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> taken priſoner, and <hi>Peter</hi> by this victory, reſtored to his Kingdome. The Prince offered to giue <hi>Bertrand</hi> his liberty without ranſome, ſo he would ſerue <hi>Henry</hi> no more, which he refuſed, becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> had murthered the Queene his wife,
<hi>Blanche de Burbon,</hi> and married a <hi>Sarizen</hi> kings daughter, the better to ſtrengthen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and had renounced the Catholicke faith. Then the Prince asked him whither he would goe if he were at liberty: he ſaid, where he would ſoone recouer his <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13712:9"/>loſſe, and deſired the Prince to aske him no further. Well, ſaid the Prince, conſider what ranſome you will giue me, for I referre it to your ſelfe. With thankes he ſaid, he would giue him 100000 doubles of gold. The Prince thought he mocked him offering him ſo much, and ſaid he would take the fourth part. I thanke you ſaid <hi>Bertrand,</hi> and you ſhall haue 60000 doubles wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. Of which the Prince accepted. Then ſaid <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trand,</hi> very conſtantly and confidently, <hi>Henry</hi> may now ſay and brag, that he ſhall die King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> for I will Crowne him, whatſoeuer it coſt me. The Prince was aſtoniſhed at his ſo haughty ſpeeches, yet vſed him very houourably, and gaue him his liberty, whereupon hee paid his ranſome, by the helpe of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And after ſiue battels, tooke <hi>Peter</hi> priſoner, put him to death, and made <hi>Henry</hi> King. The Priuernates warring againſt the
<hi>Romans,</hi> and not able to reſiſt their forces, ſent their Ambaſſadours to <hi>Rome,</hi> to demand peace: but becauſe they had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the Treaties of Peace before time, ſome thought it not fit to yeeld to their demand, and to conclude a Peace with thoſe that would not keepe it. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ambaſſadours were asked, what puniſhment they had (in their iudgement) deſerued for breaking the Peace before. To which one of the Ambaſſadours anſwered, that the Priuernates had deſerued the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which thoſe deſerue, that thinke themſelues worthy of freedome and liberty, and hate ſlauery and bondage.</p>
               <p>Some thought this anſwer too proud and perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for men ouercome: neuertheleſſe they were asked againe, if that they being pardoned for their former breach of peace, would fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenceforth keep the Peace granted them: to which the Ambaſſadours anſwered againe very conſtantly, that if they gaue them a good peace, they would faithfully and perpetually keepe it: but if they gaue them an euill peace, it ſhould not long <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13712:10"/>continue. Vpon this anſwer, diuers of the Senate were moued, but the greateſt part did not condemne them for this conſtant and reſolute anſwer, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the Ambaſſadour ſpake as a free man, and that euery one in bondage will ſeeke for liberty, therefore it was concluded that the Priuernates ſhould haue ſuch a peace, as they ſhould be admitted and receiued for Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> and enioy the ſame liberty and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge as the City of <hi>Rome</hi> did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agiges,</hi> King of the <hi>Cretians,</hi> about to giue battell to the <hi>Licaonians,</hi> his Captaines told him that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were too great in number, but he not feared ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, nor any thing changed, ſaid, that he that would raigne ouer many, muſt fight with many.
<hi>Leouidas</hi> likewiſe, ſonne to <hi>Anaxandridas,</hi> when his men told him fighting in battell, that the Arrowes of his enemies were ſo many as they couered the Sunne, was not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid thereby but conſtantly continuing his fight ſaid, then ſhall we fight vnder their ſhadow. And the great Prince <hi>Bias,</hi> falling by chance in the danger of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the
<hi>Athenians,</hi> and being asked of his Captaines, what they ſhould do, he ſeeing their feare and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, was not moued, but anſwered, that they ſhould report to the liuing, that he dyed figthing, and hee would report to the dead, that they went away flying. <hi>Scipio,</hi> though hee got the victory againſt <hi>Antiochus:</hi> yet was he not changed, but gaue him the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of peace he had offered him before the victory. <hi>Spurius Seruilius,</hi> Conſull, being accuſed before the people for the ſame matter, for which they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mned <hi>Menemius,</hi> his fellow Conſull, (who through griefe thereupon dyed) was of that conſtancy and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as he freed himſelfe, and condemned the people for their proceeding againſt <hi>Menemius. Perſes,</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> who ouerthrone by <hi>Paulus Emilius,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Captaine, was brought before him priſoner.
<hi>Emilius</hi> did riſe out of his ſeat, to receiue and honour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13712:10"/>him as a great Prince falne into that miſery by the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Fortune. But <hi>Perſes,</hi> not conſtant in magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, caſt himſelfe at his feet vpon the ground, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch baſe and abiect requeſts, vnſeeming for a King, as <hi>Emilius</hi> ſaid to him. Alas poore man thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeſt fortune, and chargeſt thy ſelfe, vnworthy of that honour thou haſt had before, being ſo baſe min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which hath made thee an vnworthy aduerſary of the <hi>Romans.</hi> But
<hi>Creſſus,</hi> King of the <hi>Lydians,</hi> being to be put to death by
<hi>Cyrus,</hi> ſhewed ſuch conſtancy and reſolution, (remembring
<hi>Solon</hi>) as <hi>Cyrus</hi> forgaue him: reſtored him, and made him one of his chiefeſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours. And <hi>Pelopidas,</hi> priſoner in the hands of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> King of the <hi>Phocians,</hi> ſent him word that he marueiled why he put his Citizens to death, and not him.</p>
               <p>The Tyrant wondring at his great conſtancy, asked why he made ſuch haſte to dye. To the end (ſaid he) that thou being yet more hated of God and man, then thou art, may the ſooner be deſtroyed. <hi>Leaena,</hi> priuy to the conſpiracy of <hi>Hermodius</hi> and <hi>Ariſtogiton,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, againſt the Tyrant of <hi>Athens,</hi> would neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, nor accuſe any, but bit of her tongue, and ſpit in the Tyrants face. In memory of which conſtancy, and ſecrecy, they erected a Lyoneſſe of braſſe without a tongue, at the entry of the Caſtle.
<hi>Zeno</hi> likewiſe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for conſpiring the death of
<hi>Diomedes</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, accuſed the Tyrants beſt friends, to make him more afraid, and faining to tel him ſome thing of them in his eare, he bit off his noſe. Then being beaten in a morter, to make him confeſſe, he bit off his owne tongue (with a ſingular conſtancy) becauſe hee ſhould accuſe no body. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> the Philoſoher did the like. A Prince therefore ſhould be conſtant, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for all fortunes. For
<hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, that as a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning workman can faſhion an Image of any kinde of matter: ſo a wiſe man ſhould be conſtant, and take in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13712:11"/>good part all kinde of fortune: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith hee)
<hi>as fire tryeth gold, ſo doth aduerſity and croſſe fortune, a man of valour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6 <hi>A Prince to be ſecret.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is neceſſary that a Prince ſhould vſe great ſecreſie in all his actions: for <hi>Valerius</hi> ſaith, that ſecreſie is the beſt and ſureſt bond, for by it great matters may be wrought, and without it Princes deſignements eaſily croſſed. Therefore the <hi>Frenchman</hi> hath a prouerbe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Que ta chemiſene ſache ta guyſe.</hi> Let not thy ſhirt know thy ſecret. <hi>Peter,</hi> K. of <hi>Arragon,</hi> being asked what he would do with a great Nauy he had prepared, (with which afterward he recouered <hi>Sicily</hi> from the
<hi>French</hi>) ſaid, that if he thought his ſhirt did know it, he would burne it. <hi>Hanniball</hi> flying from <hi>Neron, Neron</hi> left his Army neere vnto him, and went himſelfe ſecretly with a reaſonable force to ioyne with <hi>Liuius</hi> againſt <hi>Aſdru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal,</hi> whoſe Army they ouerthrew, killed him, &amp; 56000 of his men, and tooke priſoners 5400. Which done, <hi>Neron</hi> was returned to his Campe againe, before hee was knowne to be abſent. At another time the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> vſed ſuch ſecreſie, as King <hi>Eumenes</hi> demaunding of them aide againſt King
<hi>Perſeus,</hi> it was neuer known what was demanded, nor what was anſwered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the warre was ended which the <hi>Romans</hi> made at his requeſt. The Kings of <hi>Perſia</hi> puniſhed to death thoſe that diſcouered any thing determined vpon in counſell. And in <hi>Darian,</hi> a place in the <hi>Indies,</hi> they will neuer diſcouer any ſecret, eſpecialy the ſpies, for what torment ſoeuer. Both <hi>Leaena</hi> and
<hi>Zeno,</hi> before mentioned, were greatly commended for their ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as well as for their conſtancy. <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> reading a letter of great ſecreſie, one <hi>Epheſtion</hi> being in principall fauour with him, preſumed to looke on, and to reade it alſo.
<hi>Alexander</hi> would not debarre him, <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13712:11"/>but the letter being read, tooke his Ring, and with it ſealed <hi>Epheſtions</hi> mouth, ſaying, that hee who would charge himſelfe with another mans ſecret, ought to haue his mouth cloſe, and ſealed. King <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> greatly fauouring <hi>Philipides,</hi> bid him aske what hee would, and it ſhould be granted him. <hi>Philipides</hi> ſaid, I will accept of any fauour you will beſtow of mee, ſo you commit not your ſecret to me: thinking it fitteſt for a King to keepe his ſecret to himſelfe, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt for another not to know it. So had it been happy for
<hi>Fuluio,</hi> if he had neuer knowne the Emperours ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, for the Emperor <hi>Octauian</hi> committing a ſecret to him, he diſcouered it to his wife, whereof the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour getting notice, was offended with him.
<hi>Fuluio</hi> vnderſtanding thereof, and in deſpaire of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours fauour, told his wife that he would kill himſelfe. You haue reaſon, ſaid ſhe, ſeeing in ſo many yeeres you haue not knowne my imperfection, or if you did know it, to truſt it: but though the fault be yours, yet will I be firſt puniſhed, and ſo killed her ſelfe: then <hi>Fuluio</hi> did the like. The Poets fained <hi>Tantalus</hi> to be in hell, hauing about him water, &amp; the fruits he deſired to eat, which as he offered to take, fled from him alwayes: and this was his puniſhment, for reuealing that which was by the gods determined in Counſell. They feigned like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Siſiphus</hi> to be in like ſort puniſhed in Hell, for the ſame offence, carrying a ſtone vpon his ſhoulders vp a hill, and comming to the top, the ſtone alwayes falleth from him downe againe, which he returneth to fetch, and ſo neuer reſteth. Therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, that a Counſellour ought to ſpeake much to himſelfe, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to others, for feare of diſcouering any ſecret. So that ſecreſie is moſt requiſite, both in a Prince, and in his Counſellours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13712:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>A Prince to be Liberall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LIberality is alſo neceſſary and moſt commendable in a Prince, for it is the bond to oblige all men to him, both friends and foes: for which vertue the Emperour <hi>Titus</hi> was moſt commended, who laboured by liberality to deface the report againſt his father for his couetouſneſſe, and alwayes ſaid, that a man ought not to goe away ſad from the face of a Prince. And remembring one night that he had ſhewed no liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that day towards any, ſighed, ſaying: my friends I haue loſt this day. <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> kept bookes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he commanded to be written, the ſeruice which euery one did him, to the end he might reward them. <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> going to the Conqueſt of <hi>Aſia,</hi> gaue moſt of his liuing and Kingdome to his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, reſeruing hope to himſelfe. And hee being in Aegypt, a poore man asked him ſomething towards the marriage of his daughters. <hi>Alexander</hi> gaue him a City very populous and rich. Sir, ſaid the poore man, you miſtake me, or vnderſtand me not. No, ſaid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> but know, though thou be poore
<hi>Biantius</hi> in asking, that I am <hi>Alexander</hi> in giuing. <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> before the Ciuill warre, was ſo liberall to get fauour and loue of the people, as he grew thereby 750000 Crownes in debt. <hi>Cato,</hi> for all the Townes he wonne in <hi>Spaine,</hi> did neuer take any thing for himſelfe, but gaue all amongſt his Souldiers, ſaying: that a Captaine ought not to ſeeke any thing in his charge, but honour and glory. <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> was ſo liberall, as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned riches, for in fifty foure yeeres that he liued, he did neuer buy nor ſell any thing, nor made any buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, neither was there found in his houſe after his death, aboue thirty three pound weight of plate. <hi>Marcus Curius,</hi> Conſull, who had thrice triumphed, was of the like diſpoſition, for all poſſeſsions he had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13712:12"/>was but a little meane houſe in the Countrey where he liued for the moſt part, when publike affaires did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him, labouring and tylling that little ground hee had himſelfe. And when certaine Embaſſadours were ſent to viſite him, they found him dreſsing a Raddiſh for his ſupper. And they preſenting him a great ſumme of money from the Commonalty, he refuſed it ſaying: he held it farre more honourable to command them that had gold, then to haue it himſelfe. <hi>Lutius Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> did the like for after he had been Dictator, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed with greater pompe then euer did any before him, yet returned he to his poore houſe againe, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all liuing and riches the Senate offered him. For riches and treaſure is but a clog, and a heauy burthen to a wiſe man: which made all the Philoſophers to contemne wealth. For <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, he that honoureth riches, deſpiſeth wiſedome. <hi>Policrates</hi> beſtowed fiue Talents for a gift, vpon one <hi>Anacreon,</hi> who for two nights after, was ſo troubled with care how to keepe them, and how to beſtow them, as he carried them backe againe to <hi>Policrates,</hi> ſaying: they were not worth the paines which he had already taken for them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Prince ſhould not care how to lay vp, but how to lay out with honour and wiſedome. <hi>For the liberall perſon ſhall haue plenty,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi>
11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>A Prince not to be couetous.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd as by liberality a Prince may attaine to great honour: ſo by couetouſneſſe he may bring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to vtter deſtruction. For the Emperour <hi>Pertinax</hi> was a very good and vertuous Prince, ſauing that he was extreme couetous and miſerable: inſomuch that wheras he ſhould haue rewarded the men of War, who did aduance him to the Empire, he took penſions from diuers of them, which <hi>Traian</hi> his Predeceſſor, had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, for which, and for his miſerableneſſe, he was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13712:13"/>killed by his Souldiers. So was likewiſe <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> and his mother alſo, for the ſame vice. As in like manner were the Emperour <hi>Galba,</hi> and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Mauricius.</hi> And the Emperour <hi>Phocas</hi> by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery was the ruine and diſsipating of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, for in his time there fell from the Empire,
<hi>France, Germany, Spaine,</hi> the greateſt part of <hi>Italy, Eſclauonia,</hi> the greateſt part of <hi>Affrica, Armenia, Arabia, Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Thracia, Aſſyria, Meſopotamia, Egypt,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries. <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11, King of <hi>France,</hi> was ſo miſerable, as he was contemned of all Strangers, and cauſed rebellion in his own Countrey, for he put away all the Gentlemen of his houſhold, and vſed his Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor for his Herauld of Armes, his Barber for his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, and his Phyſitian for his Chancellour, and in deriſion of other Kings, he wore a greaſie hat of the courſeſt Wooll, and in his Chamber of accounts, in a bill was ſet downe 20 Souz for a paire of ſleeues to his old doublet, and 15 Denieers for greaſe to his Bootes. He increaſed the charge vpon his Subiects, three milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more then any of his Predeceſſors had done: For which he was mightily hated. <hi>Calipha,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> hauing filled a Tower with Siluer, Gold, Iewels, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, and being in Warre with <hi>Allanus,</hi> King of the
<hi>Tartarians,</hi> was ſo euill ſuccoured by his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people, becauſe he was ſo miſerable, and would not giue them their pay, as he was taken in his owne City, and by <hi>Allanus</hi> committed to priſon, in the foreſaid Tower, who ſaid vnto him: if thou hadſt not kept this Treaſure ſo couetouſly, but hadſt diſtributed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thy Souldiers, thou mighteſt haue preſerued thy ſelfe, and thy City: now therefore enioy it at thine eaſe, and eate, and drinke thy fill, ſeeing thou haſt loued it ſo well. And ſo let him die in the middeſt of his riches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13712:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>A Prince to be learned.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough it be not good that a Prince ſhould be too great a Scholler, yet it is neceſſary that he ſhould haue ſome learning: for
<hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, that neither can ignorant men, nor thoſe that ſpend all their life in ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, gouerne a Common-wealth. For great learned men are perplexed to reſolue vpon affaires, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many doubts, full of reſpects and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons The City therefore of <hi>Norenberg,</hi> did not admit any great learned man into their Counſell, but had ſome notable learned men, with whom they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, vpon any doubt that might ariſe in the Counſell. The <hi>Vrſins</hi> likewiſe in <hi>Italy,</hi> would neuer permit any learned man to gouerne their Common-wealth. Yet <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith, That wit without learning, is like to a tree without fruit. It is requiſite therefore, that both the Prince, and his gouernours ſhould be learned, as well the better to vnderſtand their duties towards God, the Lawes of the Realme, the gouernment of other Common-wealthes, and their Ambaſſadours, and the Art of Stratagems of Warre. And a Prince ſhould nouriſh and cheriſh all learning, for the attaining of all Arts and knowledge. And to that end <hi>Ptolemeus,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> made a moſt famous Library in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of 200000 Volumnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>A Prince to be religious.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt aboue all things, Religion is moſt requiſite in a Prince, that he be carefull to ſerue daily the King of Kings, who will proſper him on his Kingdome in earth, ſo he ſeekes the Kingdome of heauen, which hee muſt firſt ſeeke for, as appeareth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. And in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. a King is commanded, after he be placed in his Kingdome, to reade the <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> that he may <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13712:14"/>learne to feare God, and to keepe his words and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which are written in the Law, ſo doing, a Prince ſhall proſper, for
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith: <hi>God preſerueth the ſtate of the righteous. and is a ſhield to them that walke vprightly,</hi> Prou. chap. 2. <hi>Truſt therefore</hi> (ſaith he againe, Prouerbes, chapter 3.) <hi>in God with all thine heart, and leane not to thine owne wiſedome.</hi> So <hi>Iacob, Moſes, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Elizeus,</hi> did not truſt in themſelues, but onely by their prayers and truſt in GOD pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt their enemies. And King <hi>Dauid,</hi> though he laboured by humane diligence to defend himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Abſolon,</hi> yet eſpecially ſought to moue God to mercy, by prayer, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 15. The Emperour <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> being in <hi>Almany</hi> with his Army, was inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a dry Countrey, by his enemies, who ſtopped all the paſſages, that he &amp; his Army were like to periſh for want of water. The Emperors Lieutenant ſeeing him ſo diſtreſſed, told him, that he had hard, that the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s could obtaine any thing of their God by their Prayers. Whereupon the Emperour hauing a Legion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in his Army, deſired them to pray to their God for his and the Armies deliuery out of that danger. Which they preſently did, and incontinent, a great thunder fell amongſt the enemies, and abundance of water vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Romans,</hi> wherby their thirſt was quenched, and the enemy ouerthrowne without any fight. But pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will not auaile euery Chriſtian, vnleſſe he walke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, for God wil not heare the prayers of thoſe that lye and wallow in ſinue, as appeareth <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. And
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. <hi>Jf J finde iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not heare me.</hi> And God ſaith, <hi>when you ſhall extend and lift vp your hands, I will turne mine eyes from you, and when you ſhall multiply your prayers, I will not heare you, for your hands are full of bloud, I ſaias, chap.</hi> 1. Therefore if a man be in wicked or bloudy ſinne, his prayer is in vaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13712:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. <hi>A Prince not to ſhed innocent blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT behoueth therefore a Prince to be vertuous, and to haue ſpeciall care that he put not his hand in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, neither by tyranny, malice, ambition, polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or vpon falſe reports and informations. For, to be a Tyrant, is odious to God and man, and to bring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to an euill end. As the Emperour <hi>Nero,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had put to death his mother <hi>Agrippina,</hi> his wife <hi>Octauia,</hi> his brother
<hi>Brittannicus,</hi> and his Maſter <hi>Seneca.</hi> Beſides many others, being proclaimed an enemy to the Common-wealth, could get no body to kill him, but was glad to kill himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>Turpiter vixi, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius morior.</hi> The Emperour <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> amongſt other his tyrannies, cauſed at his dinner and ſupper or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, one to cut off before him the heads of poore priſoners, wherein he tooke great pleaſure: in the end he himſelfe was killed by his men, who conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.
<hi>Nabis</hi> the Tyrant, who vſurped the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the
<hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> ſent for eighty of their yong Princes, and without any cauſe put them all to death. And ſhortly after, <hi>Alexamenes,</hi> vnder pretence to ſerue him, with ſome company, ſuddenly ſtrucke him off from his horſe, and killed him. And as theſe tyrants had their iuſt rewards, ſo all others had the like meaſure. And for their wicked inſtruments, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple oftentimes did Iuſtice vpon them. For
<hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth, that the wicked Counſellors, and Inſtruments of
<hi>Apollodus,</hi> of <hi>Phalaris, Dionyſius, Nero,</hi> and other ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, were cruelly tormented to death by the people, and iuſtly, ſaith he, becauſe they, who corrupt, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Prince, deſerue as much to be abhorred of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, as thoſe who ſhould poyſon a publicke Spring, or Fountaine, whereof all the people doe drinke. But ſometimes thoſe Princes that doe vſe inſtruments for their murthers will not auow their Commiſsion, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13712:15"/>but doe themſelues many times put them to death whom they imployed therein, ſometimes ſecretly, ſometimes publikely, either to rid themſelues of the ſuſpition and infamy thereof, or for feare of diſcouery. As <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> at his fathers Funerals, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded publike Iuſtice to be done vpon thoſe, who himſelfe had ſecretly imployed to kill him: The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Tiberius,</hi> did not onely diſſauow his Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, giuen to a Souldier to kill
<hi>Agrippa,</hi> but put to death <hi>Seianus,</hi> his ſpeciall fauourite, and inſtrument of his miſchiefe. <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> did the like by a fauourite of his. And let no Prince thinke that he can ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue his matters, but in the end truth will be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and knowne to the world: and through ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, many haue ſhewed themſelues very barbarous and bloudy, as <hi>Tullia,</hi> daughter to <hi>Seruius,</hi> ſeeing her ſelfe married to <hi>Aruus,</hi> a man of milde diſpoſition, and her ſiſter of a gentle ſpirit, married to <hi>Lucius Tarquinius,</hi> who was ambitious, and ſhe not enduring to be thus matched, killed her husband <hi>Aruus,</hi> and her ſiſter, and then married <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> whom ſhe perſwaded to kill her father <hi>Seruius,</hi> to haue the Kingdome, and ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſtreets when he was killed, went with her Coach very inhumanely, ouer his body, that his bloud beſprinkled her cloathes.
<hi>Soliman,</hi> King of the Turks, when he heard the great noyſe and ſhout of ioy his Army made for the returne of his ſonne <hi>Sultan Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> out of <hi>Perſia,</hi> cauſed him preſently to be ſtrangled in his outward Chamber, and his dead body to be caſt out before the whole Army and one to cry with a loud voyce, that there was but one God, and one <hi>Sultan</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth. He put to death alſo <hi>Sultan Soba,</hi> becauſe he wept for his brother, and <hi>Sultan Mahomet,</hi> his third ſonne, becauſe he fled for feare, leauing one onely aliue to auoyde the inconuenience of many Lords. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Seuerus,</hi> hauing vanquiſhed <hi>Albinus</hi> and <hi>Niger,</hi> his Competitor in the Empire, embrued with blood, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13712:15"/>put a great number to death, and told his ſonne <hi>Geta,</hi> that he would not leaue him an enemy. <hi>Geta</hi> asked him, if thoſe he put to death, had neither parents, friends, nor kinsfolke, yes, ſaid the Emperour, a great number. Then ſaid <hi>Geta,</hi> you will leaue vs many moe enemies then you take from vs. His ſonne
<hi>Baſſianus,</hi> hauing murthered his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> to haue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire alone, and doubting that the Senate would greatly miſlike thereof, made a ſhew that he was ſorry for his brothers death, and that he did it by the perſwaſion of <hi>Letus,</hi> his fauourite, whom therefore he put to death, and all thoſe that did aſsiſt him in that action, likewiſe all thoſe that were friends to <hi>Geta,</hi> leſt they ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt him, yet in the end he was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> hauing vniuſtly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered twenty foure of his Barons, could neuer ſleepe quietly for repreſentation of their ſhapes, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vexed him in his dreames. And in the end hee fell into that feare of the <hi>French,</hi> as leauing his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his ſonne, he fled into
<hi>Spaine,</hi> to liue a in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, making ſuch haſte as he would take nothing with him. And his men perſwading him to ſtay two or three dayes, to make his prouiſion: no, no, ſaid hee, let vs be gone, doe you not heare how all the world cryes <hi>France, France?</hi> Hee knew himſelfe to be ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. King <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> murthered his nephew, and in the end was murthered himſelfe. <hi>Richard,</hi> likewiſe, Duke of
<hi>Gloceſter,</hi> murthered his two nephews, ſonnes to <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, to make himſelfe King, and after was ſlaine in battell by
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth: for blood re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires blood, and let a bloody Prince neuer looke for better end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>A Prince to be circumſpect in giuing credit to reports.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt many Princes haue been mightily abuſed by falſe reports, and wrong informations, yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13712:16"/>by the neareſt and deareſt vnto them, and thoſe that ſhould be moſt faithfull.
<hi>Dauid</hi> therefore prayed God to deliuer him from wicked lips, and a lying tongue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. And in <hi>Eccle.</hi> 31. we are warned to take heed of our children, and of our houſhold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. And in the ſixt chapter, it is ſaid, <hi>Seperate thy ſelfe from thine enemies, and beware euen of thy friends: for where a man doth truſt the moſt, there he may ſooneſt be deceiued.</hi> As was the Emperour <hi>Glaudius,</hi> a tymorous man, and gouerned moſt by his wife <hi>Meſſaline,</hi> and by one
<hi>Narciſſus,</hi> who, of a ſlaue he had made free, and had familiar credit with <hi>Meſſaline.</hi> This Empreſſe became enamoured of a yong Gentleman, a <hi>Roman</hi> of a Noble houſe, called <hi>Appius Sillanus,</hi> and ſeeing that by no meanes ſhe could draw him to ſatisfie her wanton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, ſhe practiſed with <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> that they both early one morning ſhould come to the Emperour, and tell him that they dreamed that <hi>Sillanus</hi> went about to kill him, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they did one after the other; &amp; <hi>Meſsaline</hi> had giuen commandement, that
<hi>Sillanus</hi> at that inſtant ſhould come to ſpeake with the Emperour. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Sillanus</hi> innocently came, and knocked at the Emperours chamber doore: which the Emperour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and perſwaded by them that their dreams were true, and that he came then to kill him, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Sillanus</hi> preſently to be put to death, which was done.
<hi>Salome,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Herod,</hi> King of <hi>Jury,</hi> perſwaded him that the Queene his wife ſought to poyſon him, and brought certaine falſe witneſſes to confirme her report, to which, the King giuing credit put his Queen to death. But this wicked ſiſter, not ſatisfied with this fearing that the Kings two ſonnes would reuenge their mothers death, perſwaded the King, that they were practiſing how to kill him, for putting their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to death. The King fearing the Authority of the Emperour, if he ſhould put them to death, brought them before <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> who knowing their <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13712:16"/>innocency by their weeping, &amp; great lamentation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be dutifull to their father, &amp; their father to make much of them, and ſo diſmiſſed them; but the Kings ſiſter inuented new matter againſt them, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her brother to ſend the Emperor word theref, which he did: then the Emperor gaue him authority to puniſh them as he thought good, whereupon the King put them both to death. But after vnderſtanding the truth, and that
<hi>Antipater,</hi> his ſonne by another wife, practiſed all this with his ſiſter, he put him to death, &amp; within few dayes after dyed himſelfe, his intrailes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inflamed, and thereby his bowels rotted, raging at theſe accidents. <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> put to death his owne ſonne <hi>Demetrius,</hi> vpon the falſe report and accuſation of
<hi>Perſius</hi> his baſe ſonne, and after, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding how he was abuſed, dyed raging. <hi>Adel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan,</hi> firſt Monarch of
<hi>England,</hi> after the entry of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> through the falſe report of his fauourite, put his owne brother to death. <hi>Francis,</hi> Duke of <hi>Britaine,</hi> put his brother <hi>Giles</hi> to death, vpon the falſe report of thoſe that were meſſengers betwixt them, and after, he vnderſtanding the truth, put them to death alſo. Therefore as in 1
<hi>Iohn</hi> 4. it is ſaid: <hi>Beleeue not euery ſpirit, but proue the ſpirits whether they be of God, or not:</hi> So a Prince ſhould duly and throughly examine report, whether it be true or not, before he giue credit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and eſpecially if it concernelife: for innocent bloud doth cry to God for reuenge, as appeareth in the <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6. ſaying: <hi>How long, Lord holy, and iuſt, iudgeſt thou not, and reuengeſt thou not our bloud on them that dwel vpon the earth.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the hands which ſhed innocent blood, are moſt odious in the ſight of God,</hi> Prou. ch. 4. Likewiſe <hi>Dauid</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 65.
<hi>That God doth abhorre abloody man.</hi> Therefore <hi>Junenal</hi> ſaith, that euery ſtay which is made to giue life to man, is good. And he that doth vſe to examine a report, made vnto him, that toucheth a mans reputation, ſhall free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13712:17"/>from lyars, for a lye cannot abide examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13. <hi>A Prince to be mercifull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Prince therefore ſhould incline himſelfe to mercy, and pardon iniuries, and auoyd the vices which may draw him to blood, which chiefly are ambition, pride, choller, and ſubiection to a woman. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, that forgiuneſſe is a valiant kind of reuenge. And the more powerfull a man is, the more is his honour to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue. And <hi>Pittacus</hi> the Philoſopher doth affirme, that pardon is better then reuenge: the one (ſaith he) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proper to the ſpirit, the other to a cruell beaſt. Therefore <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> ſaid, that a man wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had need of a more noble heart to forgiue, then to reuenge. And <hi>Cicero</hi> did more commend <hi>Caeſar</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercomming his owne courage, in pardoning
<hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> then for the great victories againſt his enemies. The Emperor <hi>Adrian,</hi> attaining to the Empire, forgot and put away all the enemies hee had before. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that after he was Emperour, meeting one of his enemies, would not touch him, but ſaid to him, thou art eſcaped.
<hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> hauing many enemies, by reaſon of the ciuill warre, did not onely pardon them, but aduanced them to dignities and offices: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wonne their loue, and made them faithfull. <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi> hauing ouerthrowne <hi>Splendius,</hi> Generall of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineers againſt
<hi>Carthage,</hi> pardoned the priſoners, and offered them ſeruice, or liberty to returne to their countrey, which got him great honour, and loue of many of his enemies. <hi>Scipio Affircanus,</hi> ſet at liberty all the Hoſtages he found in new <hi>Carthage,</hi> after he had wonne it by aſſault ſaying, He had rather bind men to him by good deeds, then by feare. And amongſt the Hoſtages, there was a maruellous beautifull young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who was contract to <hi>Allucius,</hi> Prince of the <hi>Celti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berians:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13712:17"/>Scipio</hi> commanded them both to be brought before him, and her parents came with great treaſure to redeeme her by ranſome. But
<hi>Scipio</hi> ſaid to <hi>Alluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> my friend, vnderſtanding of the loue betwixt this Lady and you, I haue kept her for you, not touched in honor, &amp; for recompence of this fauour, I pray you be a friend to the
<hi>Romans.</hi> Her parents then preſented <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> with great treaſure, which through much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity he was content to take, but beſtowed it preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon <hi>Allucius,</hi> who, not long after came to ſerue <hi>Scipio,</hi> with 1400 horſe. <hi>Scipio</hi> likewiſe by pardoning <hi>Maſsima,</hi> his vncle <hi>Maſsiniſſa</hi> became and continued a friend to the <hi>Romans.</hi> So that mercy bringeth friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and cruelty hatred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14. <hi>A Prince not to be proud.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PRide was the fall of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the ouerthrow of
<hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and the ruine of many a Prince, for, <hi>nemo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbus amat ſuperos, nec amatur ab illis.</hi> A proud man lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the gods, nor is beloued of them. Pride pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth, ſometimes cruelty, but alwayes ſhame; for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>when pride commeth, then commeth ſhame, but with the humble is wiſedome,</hi> Prou. 11. <hi>Therefore God reſiſteth the proude, and giueth grace to the humble, Iam.</hi> 3.
<hi>Allades,</hi> King of the <hi>Latines,</hi> contemning the gods, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed how to make a noyſe like thunder and lightning, to make the people feare him as a god: but thunder and lightning falling vpon his houſe from heauen, and a Lake ioyning vpon his houſe, ouerflowing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, he and his family were were all ſwallowed vp. <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> after he was Emperour, grew ſo proud, as he was therefore killed by the Senators in the Senate. And the Emperour <hi>Domitian</hi> was ſo proud, as that hee commanded in all his Proclamations and publicke ſpeeches, theſe words to be vſed. Be it knowne vnto you from your god and maſter; for which he was hated <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13712:18"/>of all the world, and in the end killed The Emperour <hi>Caius</hi> ſet in his palace like <hi>Jupitur,</hi> with a Scepter in one hand, and a thunderbolt in the other, and an Eagle at his ſide, a Cobbler ſeeing him, fel on a great laughter. The Emperour commanded him to be brought before him, and asked him at what he laughed; I laugh, ſaid he, to ſee thy pride and folly. The Emperour laughed alſo at his anſwer, and puniſhed him not, but delighted in his owne pride. But <hi>Philip,</hi> father to <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> to auoyde that vice, cauſed a child to cry vnto him euery day at his chamber dore, before hee went forth. <hi>Phllip,</hi> thou art a man mortall. <hi>Hieronimus,</hi> King of <hi>Cicily,</hi> being very yong, was wholly counſelled by his brother in law <hi>Andronodorus,</hi> who made him proud and arrogant and to contemne euery one, and to giue audience to none, nor to ſuffer almoſt any to haue acceſſe vnto him, but to giue himſelfe to all kinde of voluptuouſneſſe, and to be cruell and bloody.
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dronodorus,</hi> hauing brought him to this, conſpired with others againſt him. The treaſon diſcouered, and one <hi>Theodorus</hi> called in queſtion, therefore confeſſed, that he was of the conſpiracy, and being vpon the torture, knowing he muſt dye, accuſed (to be reuenged of the King) the Kings moſt faithfull friends and ſeruants. To which the King giuing credit, put them all to death, and immediately after, was killed by the Conſpirators. <hi>Andronodorus</hi> preſently ſeized vpon
<hi>Siracuſa,</hi> thinking to make himſelfe King. But he had ſuch ſucceſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as he, his wife, and all his family, and all the line of the King, were quite extirped, as well innocents, as offenders.
<hi>Timothae,</hi> a Captaine of <hi>Athens,</hi> through his pride, did attribute all his victories, onely to his owne pollicy and wiſedome. Whereupon (ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>) the gods were angry at his fooliſh ambition, and did neuer proſper him after, but all things went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and in the end hee was ſo odiouſly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that hee was baniſhed
<hi>Athens, Creſus,</hi> being <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13712:18"/>in the height of his pride, moſt ſumptuouſly ſet in his Throne, asked <hi>Solon,</hi> if euer he had ſeene a more gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and glorious ſight, yea, ſaid
<hi>Solon,</hi> both Capons, Feſants, and Peacocks, for their colours are naturall. <hi>Menecrates,</hi> a Phiſitian, becauſe he was excellent in his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt, grew ſo proud, as he cauſed himſelfe to be called <hi>Iupiter.</hi> But <hi>Philip,</hi> King of
<hi>Macedonia,</hi> to make him know himſelfe, inuited him to a banquet, and made a Table to be prouided for him by himſelfe, which <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necrates</hi> ſeeing, was very ioyfull that it pleaſed the King to do him that honour, but when he ſee that in ſtead of meat, they brought him nothing but incenſe, he was aſhamed, and departed with great anger. Yet this King grew a little proud after his conqueſt, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that he writ a ſharpe letter to <hi>Archidamus,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> who anſwered him, ſaying: If thou mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſhadow, thou ſhalt not finde it to be growne greater ſince thou didſt ouercome Pride therefore cannot make a man great but odious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15. <hi>A Prince to be humble.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHriſt did humble himſelfe for vs: therefore wee ought to humble our ſelues for Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>He that doth humble himſelfe ſhall be exalted, but he that doth exalt himſelfe ſhall be humbled, Mat.</hi> 23. Humility therfore (affirmeth <hi>Seneca</hi>) is the handmaiden of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom For a wiſeman is humble, if not humble, he is not wiſe. <hi>Caralus Magnus,</hi> to haue euer before his eies, the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of pouerty and humility, did cauſe certaine very poore men to eate alwayes in his preſence, their meat vpon the ground. The <hi>Romans</hi> had a cuſtome, that the Emperor, after a victory, was drawn in a Chariot with foure horſes, to the Capitall and a Clowne ſet beſides him in the Chariot, who ſtrucke him euery foot in the necke, ſaying: <hi>Know thy ſelfe.</hi> And when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was crowned one al wayes came to him, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13712:19"/>him, of what kind of mettall or ſtone hee would haue his Tombe made. And all this to the end the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhould be humble. The Emperour <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Magnus,</hi> was of that humility, as he excelled all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emperours and Princes whatſoeuer: Yet of that valour as he, ſubdued <hi>Licinius</hi> his Competitor, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Pagan</hi> Nations. The Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> being rebuked by S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> for a great offence, did in ſuch humility acknowledge his fault, as he did open pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance therefore, willingly in the Church, where Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was miniſtring the Sacrament, and ſo was admitted to communicate. The Emperours, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> were Princes of great humility, yet famous for their many victories. The Emperour
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Seuerus,</hi> was of that humility, as he would not ſuffer any to vſe other ſalutations to him, then to ſay, God ſaue thee
<hi>Alexander. Scipio,</hi> preuailing in <hi>Spaine</hi> againſt <hi>A ſdruball,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> called him King, which Title he refuſed, ſaying: it was ſufficient for him to be called their Generall.
<hi>Agathocles,</hi> King of <hi>Cicily,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was but a poore Potters ſonue, cauſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſerued with veſſels of earth, amongſt his veſſels of gold and ſiluer, to ſhew his humility, and what he was. <hi>Julius Caeſar, Auguſtus Caeſar, Claudius, Domitian, Galba, Traian, Alexander,</hi> and many other Princes, were of that humility, as they gaue continuall audience themſelues vnto the people, to the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and comfort of the people. And <hi>Octauius Caeſar,</hi> did fit daily in iudgement himſelfe, and did abhorre the title of Lord, inſomuch, that when ſaid to him, O good and gracious Lord he reproued him ſharply therefore. And the more humble that a man is, the more is he in the fauour of God, who, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>chapter</hi> 3. <hi>doth reſiſt the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13712:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. 16. <hi>A Prince not to exceed in anger.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd a Prince to be too paſsionate, and too cholle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, is dangerous, for choller ſometimes burneth and dryeth vp the veines, and taketh life, ſometimes it blindeth the vnderſtanding, and taketh away ſenſe and reaſon, wherby many a time ſodaine miſchiefe is done, that bringeth long and too late repentance, for the mind doth not eaſily ſee the truth (ſaith <hi>Saluſt</hi>) where paſsion and affection beareth ſway. Therefore a Prince eſpecially, ſhould learne to know himſelfe, and his imperfections: for <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, that the perfect du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a man, is firſt to know himſelfe. And the firſt Precept that was written in the Temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos,</hi> was, <hi>Know thy ſelfe.</hi> And knowing himſelfe, he muſt then labour to command himſelfe, and make reaſon rule nature. <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> did more glory that hee could command himſelfe, then in that he was a King. <hi>For he that is ſlow to anger</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) is better then the mighty man: and he that ruleth his owne mind, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he that winneth a City, Prou.</hi> 16. Yet moderate ire (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) doth ſecond valour and fortitude. To auoid choller, <hi>Athenodorus</hi> the Philoſopher, counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> neuer to do, or ſay, any thing when he was angry, before he had repeated the twenty foure letters of the
<hi>A, B, C;</hi> thinking by that time his chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler would be appeaſed.
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginius,</hi> being choſen Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hoſte, refuſed it, fearing to exceed in choller againſt <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> his enemy. <hi>Crotis,</hi> King of <hi>Thracia,</hi> hauing a preſent brought vnto him, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faire veſſels of glaſſe moſt curiouſly wrought, after he had well recompenced the gift, did breake them all himſelfe of purpoſe; fearing leſt through choller, (to which he was ſubiect) he ſhould too ſeuerely puniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his ſernants, if they by chance ſhould breake any of them. But the Emperour <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinian</hi> was ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13712:20"/>with choller, that he fell into ſuch a rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt certaine Ambaſſadours, as he loſt his voyce and ſpeech, and ſo was carried to his bed and let ten blood, but bled not, choller hauing burned and dryed vp the veines, and ſo dyed.</p>
               <p>Patience therefore is a happy vertue, by which a man may preſerue his body, and poſſeſſe his ſoule, ſaith Chriſt,
<hi>Luke</hi> 21. <hi>In your patience you ſhall poſſeſſe your ſoules.</hi> And to attaine to this vertue, <hi>Diogenes</hi> asked almes of the Images in <hi>Athens,</hi> to make him take deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all patiently.
<hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> being told that one railed on him, was not moued, but ſaid, whe I am abſent let him beate me alſo. And <hi>Socrates,</hi> being abuſed, ſpurned, and kicked by an inſolent fellow, and ſeeing his friends offended therewith, ſaid: How now my Maſters, if an Aſſe had kicked and giuen mee a rap on the ſhinnes, would you haue me to yerke out, and to kicke him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? <hi>Antigonus,</hi> hearing his Souldiers reuile him behind his pauillion, ſaid to them, you knaues, could you not goe a little further off, when you meant to raile vpon me? One <hi>Nicanor</hi> rayled vpon
<hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> for which his Counſell wold haue had him ſeuerely puniſhed, but the King very patiently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, firſt let vs ſee whether the fault be in him or in vs. And vnderſtanding that
<hi>Nicanor</hi> had deſerued well, and that he had neuer giuen him any thing, ſent him a rich gift. After which, <hi>Niconor</hi> ſpoke very much good of the King: Whereupon the King ſaid to his Counſell, I ſee well that I am a better Phyſitian for backebiting then you are: and that it is in my power to cauſe either good or cuill to be ſpoken of me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13712:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. 17. <hi>A Prince to be moderate in his dyet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NAture is content with a little, therefore if a man doe either eate or drinke, more then ſufficeth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is ſuperfluous, and ingendreth euill humours, corrupteth the body, and weakneth the ſpirits and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: for <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaith, that the wit is made dul with groſſe and immoderate dealing. And <hi>Plato</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that thoſe who vſe to eat much, although they haue a good wit, yet cannot be wiſe. The reaſon is, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> becauſe the body being ful of meat, corrupteth the iudgement in ſuch ſort, as maketh a man neither fit to giue counſell, nor to gouerne in a Common-wealth, nor to doe any good worke. The Emperour, <hi>Octauius Caeſar,</hi> had therefore ordinarily at ſupper, but three diſhes of meat, and when he fared beſt he had but ſixe. And the
<hi>Egyptians</hi> in their feaſts and banquets, had a dead body dryed, brought in amongſt them, that the ſight thereof might containe them in modeſty, and make them temperate in their feeding. <hi>Ada,</hi> Queene of
<hi>Caria,</hi> ſent <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> certaine skilfull Cooks, whom he refuſed, and ſent her word, that he had better then they were; namely, for his dinner, early riſing, and walking a good while before day, and for his ſupper, a little dinner, for in thoſe dayes they did commonly eate but one meale a day, as appeareth by <hi>Plato,</hi> who, being demaunded if he had ſeene any new or ſtrange thing in <hi>Cicily,</hi> ſaid, that he had found there a Monſter of nature, which did eate twice a day, meaning
<hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> the Tyrant. <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> King of the
<hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> paſsing his Army through the Countrey of
<hi>Thracia,</hi> they preſented with meale fowle, baked meates, and all other ſorts of delicate meates and conſerues. The meale hee was willing to take, but not the reſt, yet through great intreaty, he accepted of all, and gaue all <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13712:21"/>and gaue all (ſauing the meale) to his ſlaues, and being asked why he did ſo, he ſaid, It is not conuenient for men who make profeſsion of manhood and proweſſe, to eate ſuch delicates; for by pleaſure, delicate meats and drinkes, the courage of man is abated. Therefore
<hi>Xerxes,</hi> after hee had taken the great City of <hi>Babylon,</hi> would not put the people to death, but to be reuenged of them, commanded them not to exerciſe any Armes, but to vſe and giue themſelues to all pleaſure, feaſting, and drinking. So that by this meanes, they grew to be moſt vile and baſe people, whereas before they were moſt valiant. And by the great feaſting and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in <hi>Siracuſe</hi> in <hi>Cicily,</hi> the
<hi>Romans</hi> tooke the towne and ſpoyled it. The Emperour
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itellius,</hi> was very rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous in his diet, inſomuch, as at one ſupper, he had 2000 ſeuerall kinde of fiſhes, and 7000 diſhes of foule, but what followed? Soone after hee was openly put to death by
<hi>Veſpaſian. Caligula</hi> likewiſe, in riotous ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, in making ſweet bathes, and in other vaine and friuolous expences, ſpent in one yeare, 67 millions of crownes, and in the end was killed. <hi>Nero</hi> alſo was prodigal in the like charges and banquets, &amp; ſumpuous attire, neuer wearing one garment twice. And <hi>Sabina,</hi> his wife had daily the milke of
500 Aſſes to bathe her in, but their ends were pittifull. The Emperour
<hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> was riotous in his youth, and thereby diſeaſed in his age, which forced him to vſe many Phiſitians and medicines, but could not be cured. Therefore good order and temperate dyet, prolongeth the life, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferueth wiſedome. Early riſing alſo (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) and much watching, are profitable to keepe a man in health, and to augment his wiſedome. It doth withall increaſe deuotion, for then a man ſhall find himſelfe moſt apt to ſerue God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13712:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. 18. <hi>A Prince to be continent of life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt if he ſerue his belly with immoderate, and too great delicates, and pamper his fleſh too much, it will (beſides dulling of the wit) make the fleſh rebell againſt the ſpirit, and fall to incontinency, a vice wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Prince ought to haue a ſpeciall care, that he giue not himſelfe to the luſt of the fleſh; <hi>for it is a deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fire till all be conſumed, and rooting vp the ſeed of good workes,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Iob</hi> 31. And <hi>Luxuria eneruat vires, effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat artus.</hi> It will make him weake and effeminate, and deſtroyeth both body and ſoule, loſing thereby alſo ſometimes, both life and kingdome: for by adultery,
<hi>Roderico,</hi> laſt King of the <hi>Gothes</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> committed with the wife of <hi>Iulian,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cewta,</hi> when hee was Ambaſſadour in <hi>Africke,</hi> he, for reuenge, brought the
<hi>Moores</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> who therupon ſubdued the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
<hi>Oſibright,</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> rauiſhed the wife of one <hi>Barne,</hi> who, to be reuenged, brought in the <hi>Danes,</hi> ſlew
<hi>Oſibright,</hi> and made great ſpoyle in the land. The Emperour
<hi>Claudius,</hi> married his brothers daughter, and ſhee her ſelfe poyſoned him. <hi>Siphax,</hi> King of <hi>Numidia,</hi> tranſported with the loue of <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisba,</hi> falſified his faith, loſt his Kingdome, and life in priſon. <hi>Locrine,</hi> King of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> put
<hi>Guendoline</hi> his wife away, and married <hi>Eſtreld,</hi> daughter to King <hi>Humber,</hi> but <hi>Guendoline</hi> killed her husband in battell, and drowned <hi>Eſtreld</hi> and her daughter in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne.</hi> The Emperour <hi>Commodas,</hi> kept three hundred Courtizans, and in the end by one of them, and one of his Paraſites, was ſtrangled. <hi>Childericke,</hi> the third King of <hi>France,</hi> for his libidonous life, which made him careleſſe in gouerning the Common-wealth, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. And
<hi>Lewis</hi> the ſixt, King of <hi>France,</hi> for his adultery, was poyſoned by <hi>Blanche</hi> his wife: <hi>Helioga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13712:22"/>for his libidonous and vitious life, thought hee might make an euill end, and therefore if in caſe hee ſhould be preſſed by his enemies, he had poyſon ready kept in precious ſtones: he had alſo halters of ſilke to hang himſelfe: and ſharpe kniues of precious mettall to kill himſelfe: and he built a high Tower, richly gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to breake his necke vpon, if he liſted: yet all theſe deuiſes failed him, for he was ſtrangled by his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and trailed vp and downe <hi>Rome.</hi> This is the end a libidonous Prince may looke for. But wiſe and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Princes will auoyd that vice. As did <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who hauing the wife of
<hi>Putiphar</hi> in his power, would not touch her. No more would
<hi>Abimelech</hi> faire <hi>Sara.</hi> Nor <hi>Dauid</hi> the <hi>Ebritian Sunamite.</hi> Nor <hi>Scipio</hi> the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; who was Hoſtage in
<hi>Carthage;</hi> Nor <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> the wife to <hi>Phocius:</hi> Nor
<hi>Alexander,</hi> the daughter of King <hi>Darius:</hi> Nor <hi>Auguſtus, Cleopatra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as it is hurtfull for a Prince to be allured by a woman to folly, ſo it is not good for him to be led by the counſell of a woman. For
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that part of a womans vnderſtanding in which conſiſteth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, is imperfect. Therefore neither the
<hi>Romans,</hi> nor the <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> did euer admit a woman into Councell. Yet <hi>Theodora,</hi> after the death of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the Emperour of <hi>Conſtanſtinople,</hi> was choſen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and had the onely gouernment of the Empire. Which without the helpe of any, ſhe gouerned in great peace and proſperity two yeares, and then dyed, to the great griefe of all her ſubiects, who repented them not to be gouerned by a woman.</p>
               <p>The Empreſſe likewiſe, <hi>Zenobia</hi> in
<hi>Aſia,</hi> was a moſt ſingular rare woman. For <hi>Obdinato,</hi> her husband, choſen in <hi>Aſia</hi> for their Emperour, and after killed by his kinſman ſhe tooke vpon her the gouernment, and gouerned very well. She was conſtant in her enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, faithfull of her word, liberall in her gift, iuſt in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſentence, ſeuere in puniſhment, diſcreet in her
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13712:22"/>ſpeech, graue in her determination, and ſecret in that ſhe did. She loued not to ride in a Litter, but on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe: ſhe was of ſtature tall, ſlender bodyed, her eyes great, her forehead large, her face ſomewhat pale, her mouth little, and her teeth ſmall. After ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with child, ſhee would not company with her husband, ſaying: that a woman ought not to marry for pleaſure, but onely for procreation. She did eate but once a day, and that at night: ſhe drunke no wine, but water compounded more coſtly then wine: when ſhe went to Campe, or to battell, or to skirmiſh, ſhe was armed, and euer when there was any ſeruice, ſhe would be amongſt them.</p>
               <p>In the end, the Emperour <hi>Aurelianus</hi> beſieged her, tooke her priſoner, and carried her in his triumph to <hi>Rome,</hi> yet pardoned her for her vertue and valour, and gaue her certaine poſſeſsions to liue vpon. She liued ten yeares after, as greatly honoured and beloued as
<hi>Lucretia,</hi> of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Ladies. But this is (as the
<hi>Spaniard</hi> ſaith) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na golondrina que non haze verano.</hi> One Swallow which maketh no Summer. Yet I could not but ſet downe here her perfection, ſhe being ſuch a mirrour for all Ladyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 19. <hi>A Prince to beware of Paraſites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt there is another creature about a Prince, more dangerous then a woman, and that is a flatterer, who neuer ſings other ſong then
<hi>placebo,</hi> ſoothing a Prince in whatſoeuer. <hi>Apelles</hi> drew the picture of a King (which he ſent to <hi>Ptolomeus</hi>) ſet in a chaire of Eſtate, with great hands great eares, and beſides him Ignorance, Suſpition, a Tale-teller, and Flattery: theſe will labour to be about a Prince, therefore a Prince muſt labour to auoyd them. For an enuious and backebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Tale-teller, and a Flatterer, are two moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous beaſts: for <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaith, that of wilde beaſts, a <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13712:23"/>backbiter biteth the ſoreſt, and of tame beaſts, a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Hermes,</hi> the Philoſopher ſaith, that as a Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion can change himſelfe into all colours ſauing white: ſo hath a Paraſite all points ſauing honeſty, for he win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe into fauour by any meanes, eſpecially of pleaſure, procuring any kind of mirth and delight, and by humouring the party.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> and <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> King of
<hi>Arragon,</hi> hauing each of them ſomewhat a wry necke; the one by nature, the other by cuſtome, the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Courtiers held their neckes on the one ſide. And like as wormes breed moſt of all, and ſooneſt in firme, tender, and ſweet wood: euen ſo for the moſt part, the generous and gentle natures, and thoſe mindes that are more ingenuous, honeſt, amiable and milde then others, are readieſt to receiue and nouriſh the flatterer that hangeth vpon him. And <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, that he who loueth himſelfe, and hath a good conceit of himſelfe, can be content to admit another to flatter him. But when a Paraſite ſeeth nothing to be gotten, then he is gone, being like to lice: For as theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine neuer haunt the dead, but doe leaue an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forſake the corpes ſo ſoone as the bloud is extinct and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vitall ſpirit: ſo a man ſhall neuer ſee flatterers approach to thoſe that are in decay, whoſe ſtate is cracked, and credite loſt. But where there is power and authority, and glory in the world: thither they flocke, and there they grow and ſhew themſelues moſt malicious, ſometimes by ſpeaking euill of others. For <hi>Medeus,</hi> the chiefe Captaine of the flatterers, about <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> teached his Schollers to caſt out ſlanders boldly, to bite others, for (ſaid he) though the ſoare may heale vp, yet the skarre will remaine and be euer ſeene. By theſe skarres of falſe imputations, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> being corroded and eaten, put to death <hi>Caliſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes, Parmenion,</hi> and <hi>Philocas,</hi> his true and faithfull <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13712:23"/>friends. The Emperour <hi>Commodus,</hi> after the death of his father, was led by Paraſites, and vpon their falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, put to death moſt of thoſe that were graue Counſellors to his father, and alſo many of the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and committed the gouernment of all his affaires, to <hi>Perennis,</hi> and himſelfe followed his pleaſure, which brought him to the end you heard before. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<hi>Diocleſian,</hi> baſely borne in <hi>Sclauonia,</hi> was in his youth very ambitious, and deſirous of honour, and from a poore Souldier, came to be Emperour, and then made the people honour him as a god, and to kiſſe his foot, whereon he did weare guilt ſhooes, ſet with pearle and precious ſtones after the manner of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Kings. But ſeeing in the end, himſelfe wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed by the flatterers of his Court, and that hee could take no order for them, they had him ſo beſieged in their hands, he gaue ouer the Empire, and retyred himſelfe to his houſe in
<hi>Slcauonia,</hi> where he liued euer after, a very priuate life, delighting himſelfe with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and rurall workes. But the Emperour <hi>Caligula,</hi> tooke a better courſe with his Paraſites, for one <hi>Afria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Potitus,</hi> and <hi>Afranius Secundus,</hi> made a ſhew of great ſorrow for him when he was ſicke, and ſwore by the gods that they would very willingly dye for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery. The Emperour knowing they did but flatter, ſaid then little, but being recouered, called them before him, and ſaid, my good friends, I haue found that you are in fauour with the gods, for ſince your vow for me, I haue recouered, but fearing I ſhould fall ſicke againe, if you accompliſh not your vow, I ſent for you to dye, deſiring you both to take your deaths patiently, and ſo preſently put them to death.
<hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth, that <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> the Tyrant of
<hi>Cicily,</hi> delighting in his owne Poems, asked diuers Philoſophers, how they liked them, they all flatteringly, highly commended them, ſauing one, who ſaid plainly, that it was a ſhame to heare them, they were ſo bad. Whereat the Tyrant of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, <pb n="42" facs="tcp:13712:24"/>commanded him to the Mines, there to worke amongſt the condemned men: but being releaſed by meanes of his friends, and againe in the Kings preſence, when he demaunded the opinion of the Philoſophers, in another of his Poems, and they all extolling it aboue the Skies, he cryed to the guard of the Tyrant, ſaying: Come my maſters, come carry me away to the Mines againe, for I cannot endure this fooliſh flattery. The King by chance, being then in a good humour, was not offended, but turned it to a laughter. <hi>Curtius</hi> ſaith, that the ſtates of Princes are oftner ouerthrowne by flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, then by force. It is a happy thing therefore for Princes to haue thoſe about them that will not flatter, but tell them the truth. For what (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth he that hath all? marry one to tell the truth. Therefore the Emperour <hi>Gordian</hi> ſaid, that that Prince is very vnfor tunate who hath not about him, thoſe who may plainly tell him the truth. For a King know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what paſſeth, but by relation of thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with him. <hi>Theopompus,</hi> being asked how a Prince might preſerue his Kingdome, ſaid, by giuing his friends liberty to ſpeake the truth, and in keeping his ſubiects from oppreſsion. <hi>Phocian</hi> dealt plainly and like a faithfull ſeruant with King <hi>Antipater,</hi> telling him vpon occaſion, that he would do him any ſeruice poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but could not be to him both a friend and a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> in like manner, ſeeing
<hi>Euribiades</hi> taking vp a ſtaffe to ſtrike him for his free ſpeeches, ſaid, ſtrike me, ſo you will heare me after.</p>
               <p>A Prince therefore muſt permit freedome of ſpeech, if he meane to heare the truth, and giue no care to flattery. <hi>Peſſenius Niger,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Captaine, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one praiſe and flatter him in his Oration, ſaid to him, goe, goe, write the praiſes of <hi>Marius,</hi> and <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball,</hi> &amp; other old and valiant Captaines that are dead, that we may immitate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for it is a mockry to praiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are aliue: and as for me, I will do good whilſt <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13712:24"/>I liue, and be prayſed when I am dead. Yet <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> king of <hi>Sparta</hi> ſayd, that he liked to be prayſed of thoſe friends, who would not alſo ſpare to blame him, when occaſion ſhould ſerue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20. <hi>What kind of perſons to be of a Princes Counſell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Prince ſhould be very carefull in making choyce of his Counſellors. For <hi>Plato</hi> faith, that many Princes are vndone, becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y want faithfull friends and ſeruants to counſell them. Therefore <hi>Alfred</hi> ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g of <hi>England,</hi> ſought out the wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, and moſt learned men to be about him. <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> likewiſe made choiſe of honeſt and vertnous Counſellors, and dilplaced the vitious, and ſought to know the truth of all things that paſſed in all places and Prouinces of the Empire. <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Furius</hi> opinion is, that Counſellours to a Prince ought not to be vnder thirty yeares of age, nor aboue ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For (ſayth he) before he be thirty his vnderſtanding is not ſetled, his experience llitle, his preſumption great, his heate much, his thoughts light, and not of ſufficient grauity. And that after ſixty yeares his memory faileth, his vnderſtanding weake, his experience turned to obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, his his heate little, lonſing oacaſion, his thoughts wearied, and able to take no paines nor trauell. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſome haue beene able and ſufficient enough after they paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d that age, as <hi>Camillus</hi> who though he were of very great yeares, yet was choſen Dictator: they finding his memory good, and his ſenſes perfect: So many others haue bene fince his time. And <hi>Frederieus Furius</hi> ſayth moreouer, that a Counſellour to a Prince ought to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a chollericke, or of a fanguine complexion, for that thoſe of that temper (ſaith he) are witty, haue good memory, can diſcourſe well, are of good iudgement, moſt louing, affable, loyall, liberall, and of great cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13712:25"/>and that the melancholike are baſe minded, vaine, enemies to noble thoughts, malicious, ſuperſtitious, and phantaſticall. And <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith, a Prince ought not to truſt him that is couetous, nor him that is a flatterer, nor to make a paſſionate, or a too cholericke man of his counſell, nor a drunkard, nor any that is ſubiect to a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. For it is not poſſible (ſaith he) that they ſhould keepe cloſe his ſecrets. And <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſaith, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to obtaine wiſedome and knowledge, that is in bondage to a woman: therefore the Emperour <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Seuerus</hi> would neuer admit any Counſellor, or other officer, whether he were of Noble parentage, or had done him great ſeruice, or were commended to him, vnleſſe he were of good reputation, learned, of good experience, and of good life. And better to informe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hereof, he cauſed wrightings to be ſet vp in common places of the ſtreetes, deſiring thereby the people to ſhew ſome cauſe, if they could, why ſuch a man ſhould not be admitted to ſuch a place and office, and would not ſuffer any office to be ſold, becauſe Iuſtice ſhould not be ſold. Yet the Emperor
<hi>Veſpaſian</hi> at the beginning of his raigne gaue the chiefe offices &amp; dignities to the greateſt theeues he could find, and being asked why he did ſo, anſwered, that he vſed them as a ſpunge, for when they were full he would wring them, and confiſcate all they had, and hang them. Some Princes doe place thecues in authority, not knowing them, but being diſcouered, it were happy for the common wealth, and good for the Prince, if they were vſed as <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> vſed his. And <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata placed a cruell and troubleſome Iudge at <hi>Alexandria</hi> in
<hi>Aegypt,</hi> and being told he was vnworthy to gouerne: it is true, ſayd he, and therefore I placed him there, that he may plague them as they deſerue, they being a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and wicked people, but good men are alwayes to be placed in gouernement, that the wicked by example may amend, or be puniſhed, and the good preſerued. <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13712:25"/>For
<hi>Pictatus</hi> reputed that common wealth to be well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, in which wicked men might beare no authority. And a Prince is to haue ſome for Counſell, ſome for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, for very ſeldome doth it concurre in one man to haue wit to diſoourſe well vpon any matter in Counſell, and to haue iudgement to execute that which by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is determined. The Captaine
<hi>Picinio</hi> was in conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a weake iudgement, but in executing any thing reſolued vpon by Counſell, very ready. <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>France</hi> did exceed all his Counſell in conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but in his execution was not anſwerable to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 7. did exceed all other in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; but in executing was inferiour to euery one. And as it is neceſſary that a Prince ſhould haue a graue and wiſe Counſell: ſo is it requiſite hee ſhould haue ſome about him for his pleaſure. So <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> when he went into <hi>Aſia</hi> againſt <hi>Darius,</hi> tooke with him two of his moſt ſpeciall friends and ſeruants, <hi>Craterus</hi> and <hi>Hephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> very different in complexion, and in condition: for
<hi>Craterus</hi> was graue, ſeuere and ſtoike, and only cared for matters of State and Counſell, being one of the Kings principall Counſellors. And
<hi>Hipheſtion</hi> was a yong Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of good complexion, gallant, actiue, and full of ſport, and onely cared how to recreate the King. So that
<hi>Craterus</hi> was called a friend to the King: and <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> a friend to <hi>Alexander.</hi> But a Prince had need to be very carefull in chooſing of his friend, to be inward and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with him. For
<hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> did not receiue a man to his amity and familiarity, but firſt did proue him, and ſound his virtues, fidelity and loyalty, and thoſe who hee knew to be vertuous, and that told him freely the truth in all things, and that did not flatter, and that imployed themſelues willingly and ſincerely in his affaires, and after hauing had good proofe hereof, he receiued them for his friends. <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> to try his friends, made them one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another beleeue, that he had killed a man, and they all <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13712:26"/>refuſed to endanger themſelues for him, ſauing one <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias.</hi> The Emperour <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to make proofe of his friends, made ſhew to abandon Chriſtian Religion, and to turne to Idolatry, he was inſtantly applauded by a great number, whom preſently he baniſhed the Court. For a Prince ſhall neuer want followers in any thing. The world counſelling thoſe that ſerue Princes to pleaſe them in whatſoeuer, though it redound to the loſſe of their ſoules, and ruine of the common-wealth, for ſo they ſhall obtaine honor, riches pleaſure, and quietneſſe: but what is their end? <hi>Ducunt in bonis dies ſuos, &amp; in puncto ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferna deſcenaunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> 21. <hi>They lead their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yes in pleaſure, and in an inſtant deſcend into hell. For when they ſhall ſay peace and ſecurity, then ſhall ſuddaine deſtruction come vpon them,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. <hi>Vidi impium ſuperexaltatum, &amp; eleuatum ficut Cedrum Libans, &amp; tranſiut eum. &amp; non eſt inuentus loeu eius. I did ſee the impious mightily exalted and raiſed on high as the Cedar tree, and I paſſed by, and preſently he was gone, I ſought him, and his place was not to bee found.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore affimeth, that
<hi>it is better to ſuffer torments for ſpeaking the truth, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue great rewards for flattery.</hi> And Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Feare not them that kill the body, leaſt for feare of them, thou ſpeake not the truth freely.</hi> And as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours ought to haue freedome of ſpeech: So <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus Furius</hi> doth wiſh a Prince, for tryall of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, to aske counſell ſometimes in things contray to the good of the Common wealth, and to his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Demetrius Phelarius</hi> counſelled
<hi>Ptholomeus</hi> King of Egypt, to reade bookes which treated of Kings and Common wealths, for that in them be ſhould finde many things which his Counſell and families durſt not tell hid. But <hi>Ariſteus</hi> ſaith, that the greateſt and beſt guard a Prince can haue, is to be accompanied with a <pb facs="tcp:13712:26"/>great number of iuſt and expert Counſellours, who through meere loue, ſetting their owne particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity apart, regard onely the profite and welfare of the Prince and common wealth, ſpeaking freely what they thinke. For Counſellours, ſayth <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> in one of his orations to the Senate, ſhould not be led by malice, friendſhip, anger, nor mercy. And if they concurre in one lawfull opinion, though the Prince be oppoſite, yet it is fitting he ſhould yeeld to them. For ſo did the Emperour <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> ſaying: <hi>It muſt bee as You will: for it is great reaſon, that I being but one, ſhould follow your opinion, then you being many, Wiſe and Learned, ſhould yeeld to mine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21. <hi>Not good to commit the charge of the Common wealth to one Counſellor onely.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt it is very dangerous for a Prince to be led by the aduice and counſell of one onely, or to commit the gouernement of the Common wealth to one Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour onely. And ſo <hi>Commines</hi> dath witneſſe, ſaying: that A Prince ought to haue many Counſellours, and not commit any cauſe of importance to one onely, and that all his Counſellours ſhould be equall in fauour: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if he be led onely by one, and make no accompt of the reſt, not giuing them equall hearing, he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger himſelfe, as did <hi>Hieronimus</hi> King of <hi>Cicily,</hi> who was onely counſelled by his brother in law <hi>Androno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus,</hi> who made him odious to all the Kingdome, and then killed him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stillico</hi> likewiſe gouerned all vnder the Emperour
<hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius.</hi> And to get entrance to make himſelfe Emperour, took pay from the <hi>Goths,</hi> of purpoſe to make them rebel which thereupon they did, and by the aide they got, ſpoyled <hi>Thracia, Hungaria, Auſtria, Sclauonia,</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia: <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13712:27"/>Stilico,</hi> though hee might, yet would not quite ouer throw them, whereof <hi>Honorius</hi> being informed, put to death both <hi>Stilico</hi> and his ſonne. Vnder the Emperour <hi>Commodus</hi> firſt <hi>Perennis</hi> ruled all, and for diſplacing the Nobility, and preferring baſe perſons, was killed by the ſouldiers. After him <hi>Cleander</hi> managed all, and a great famine and plague beeing in <hi>Rome,</hi> the people imputed the cauſe thereof to him, and thought to kill him: Hee to appeaſe this ſturre ranne vpon the people with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours horſe-men, and killed a great number of them. The Emperour fearing himſelfe, ſent for <hi>Cleander,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently cut off his head, and ſent it to the people, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were appeaſed, yet in the end <hi>Commodus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was killed. The Emperor <hi>Seuerus</hi> permitted <hi>Plautia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to gouerne all vnder him at his pleaſure, who in the end practiſed to kill him, and his two ſonnes. But
<hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſianus</hi> the Emperours ſonne vnderſtanding thereof, and that his Father meant to pardon him, killed him in the Emperours preſence. The Emperour <hi>Galba</hi> was a good Prince and wiſe, yet ſuffered himſelfe to be onely gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Titus Iunius, Cornelius Lacus,</hi> and
<hi>Icellus Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> who by their wicked gouernement made the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to be hated of all eſtates, and therefore the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple murthered him. This Emperour was the more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted becauſe he entertayned <hi>Halotus</hi> and
<hi>Tygenlinus,</hi> who were principall ſeruants to <hi>Nero,</hi> and inſtruments in all his wickedneſſe. So <hi>Otho</hi> likewiſe Emperor after <hi>Galba,</hi> though hee thought by good words and liberality to get the hearts of the people, yet did they hate him, for that he had ſome about him, who had beene inſtruments and Counſellors to <hi>Nero.</hi> The Kings of <hi>France</hi> for forty yeares, giuing wholly to their pleaſures, permitted the Maior of the Palace of <hi>Paris</hi> to gouerne all at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which gaue opportunity to <hi>Pipin</hi> to make himſelfe King: Who being wiſe, vertuous, and well beloued, was thereby admitted their King. But the Emperour <hi>Tyberius</hi> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:13712:27"/>giuing himſelfe to pleaſure, and committing the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Seanus,</hi> who grew proud thereof, and tooke vpon him as he had bene Emperor, and had ſtatues made him, before which they offered ſacrifice, and happy were they that had his fauour: The Emperour hearing of his pride, and inſolency, committed him to priſon: then thoſe that did moſt honour him, contemned him, and ſpoke euill of him. And the Emperour put both him, and all his children to death
<hi>Zoticus</hi> had that credite with <hi>Halingabalus,</hi> as he was held Lord ouer all the reſt, his counſell as a Law, and by his direction all Offices were ſould: Hee made Conſuls the ſonnes of ſlaues and baſe men. And King <hi>Attolus</hi> gaue himſelfe ſo to his pleaſure, as one
<hi>Phylopaemen</hi> gouerned him as hee liſted. Inſomuch that the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> when they did ſee any ſhip of <hi>Aſia</hi> come by, asked if the King was ſtill in the good grace and fauour of
<hi>Phylopaemen.</hi> But <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeauenth King of
<hi>France,</hi> hauing diuers wiſe, and faithfull Counſellours of meane parentage, at the time he had ciuill Warre with the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> (whom the Duke of <hi>Brittany</hi> ſecretly fauoured) mooued the Dukes to peace, who anſwered, if the King would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue his Counſellours from him, and take others, that they would accord. Whereuppon the Kings Councell perſwaded him to accept thereof, and they moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſed the Court, and retyred themſelues to their owne houſes, and ſo the Warre was ended. Therefore a Prince ſhould take care for the good education of his Nobility, and honour the Noble and worthy families; whereby they may continue in the Vertue and Valour of their Anceſtors, and the Prince thereby be the better ſerued. In <hi>Rome</hi> there was a Law made, called
<hi>Proſopina,</hi> by which the off-ſpring of <hi>Siluius,</hi> of
<hi>Torquatus,</hi> and of <hi>Fabricius,</hi> were more honoured and priuiledged then any other, becauſe they were ancient Families, and more vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant then others: They had a Law alſo, that thoſe who were
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13712:28"/>deſcended of wicked perſons, as of <hi>Tarquinius Superbus,</hi> of the Conſull <hi>Eſcaurus,</hi> of <hi>Catelin,</hi> of the Cenſor <hi>Faba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and of the Traytor <hi>Bicinus,</hi> ſhould beare no Office in the Common-wealth, nor dwell within the circute of
<hi>Rome.</hi> But Nobility marrying baſely, do oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. For when nature (ſayth <hi>Plato</hi>) produced man, ſhe gaue vnto him three properties of the mettals, as to thoſe that were fit to gouerne the people, the property of Gold: To them of force and valour, to defend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, the property of Siluer; and the property of Iron and Braſſe to handy-craftes men; and common people, to work and labour. And he ſayth, that marrying the Noble with the Ignoble, is to mixe good mettal with baſe mettall, which is the ouer-throw of Nobility, and changing of gouernment of the Common-wealth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he counſelleth euery o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to marry with their equals, Nobles with Nobles, and ignobles among themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22. <hi>A Prince not to place a Stanger in Authority.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Prince is alſo to haue ſpeciall regard that hee giues not a Stranger authority in the Common-wealth, nor truſt him too much. For the ancient <hi>Romanes</hi> would neuer giue any charge or Office in the Common-wealth to a Stanger: Inſomuch that after the Battell of
<hi>Cannas,</hi> for want of ſufficient men to be Senators in <hi>Rome, Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Curulius</hi> making a motion to haue had ſome of the Latis choſen for Senators, they would not agree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but all hated <hi>Spurius</hi> for that motion. And <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> King of <hi>Cicily,</hi> deſcended of the houſe of <hi>France,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a French-man his Chancellour, the Noble-men much grieued thereat, conſpired, and in one night killed all the French-men in <hi>Cicily,</hi> in <hi>Apulia,</hi> and in <hi>Calabria. Charles</hi> the 8. King of <hi>France</hi> expulſed the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of <hi>Naples</hi> by the helpe of the <hi>Neapolitanes,</hi> and placed French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in all authority and gouernment there. Whereupon <pb facs="tcp:13712:28"/>the Neapolitans grieued, made a generall reuolte, and did driue out the French-men againe. The Duke of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> hauing married an Engliſh woman was ſo affected to the Engliſh, as his ſubiects much diſliked thereof, and hee miſtruſting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, ſent for Engliſh-men to gouerne vnder him, but before they came, his owne ſubiects ſeized vpon all the Forts and Townes in <hi>Britany,</hi> and forced the Duke to flye into <hi>England.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> placing Engliſh-men in all Offices and authority in <hi>Aquitaine,</hi> made the Country-men grudge thereat, and in the end reuolte, by which meanes
<hi>Aquitane</hi> was loſt. <hi>Alexander</hi> King of the <hi>Epirots,</hi> giuing entertainement to a number of the <hi>Lucamans</hi> baniſhed out of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and after making Warre againſt their Country, thought he ſhould be well ſerued by them, who promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to yeelde their Country into his hands, but they made a ſecret compact with their Country-men to the contrary, for drawing the King into a conuenient place for their purpoſe, they ſhewed themſelues his enemies, and he ſwimming a riuer, to eſcape, in landing was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by one of them. The Emperour <hi>Gordian</hi> making an
<hi>Arabian</hi> his Lieutenant called <hi>Phillipus,</hi> a man of baſe parentage, he procured the Emperours ouerthrow, and in the end killed him moſt barbarouſly. <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> was betrayed by an <hi>Italian</hi> the Earle of <hi>Campobach,</hi> and killed before
<hi>Nancy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 23. <hi>Dangerous for a Prince to take ayde of a Stranger.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd if a Prince take ayde or ſuccours of a ſtranger ſtronger then himſelfe, he may thereby endanger his eſtate. For the
<hi>Eſterques</hi> called but to aide the Citty of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulture,</hi> ſubdued it. The <hi>Herules, Gothes,</hi> and <hi>Lombards,</hi> called into
<hi>Italy</hi> for ſuccours, became Lords thereof. So did they of
<hi>Franconia</hi> with their King <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramond;</hi> 
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13712:29"/>by the <hi>Gaules,</hi> now <hi>France.</hi> And the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> did the like by <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Turkes</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner got the Eaſt Empire; and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> called firſt in by the Emperour of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and by the States of <hi>Hungaria. Cairaam</hi> a Pyrate called by the Inhabitants of <hi>Alger,</hi> to expell the Spaniards, after hee had van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the Spaniards, ſlew <hi>Selin</hi> Prince of the Towne, and made himſelfe King, leauing the eſtate to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<hi>Aradin Barbaroſſa. Saladin</hi> a <hi>Tartarian</hi> Captaine called by the <hi>Calipha</hi> and Inhabitants of <hi>Cair,</hi> to driue the Chriſtians out of <hi>Soria,</hi> after the Victory agaynſt the Chriſtians, ſlew the <hi>Calipha,</hi> and became abſolute Lord thereof. The <hi>Romanes</hi> called into <hi>Cicily,</hi> by the <hi>Mamertins</hi> or
<hi>Campanois,</hi> to aide them, did ſubiect both them, and all
<hi>Cicily</hi> in the end. <hi>Francis</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> had a de of <hi>Soliman</hi> the great <hi>Turke,</hi> againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, who fearing by continuing the War, that the <hi>Turke</hi> might get that footing, as to ouercome all Chriſtendom, made peace with
<hi>France.</hi> But then the Turkes <hi>Baſcha</hi> being in
<hi>Marcelles,</hi> the King of <hi>France</hi> could not get him out, before hee had ſuccours from the Emperour: who was forced to ayde him. Therefore when Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour,
<hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Lewes</hi> King of
<hi>France,</hi> had entred league againſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians: Selin</hi> the great Turke, offered to ſend the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians</hi> ſuccours, which they refuſed, fearing that accepting thereof, they ſhould be in danger of the Turke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 24. <hi>A Prince to get and keepe the loue of his Subiects.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Prince therefore, to the end he may be ſtrong at home, and neede no Forraine force, ſhould alwayes reſpect his owne ſubiects (eſpecially men of worth and ſeruice) as well in peace as in VVarre, that hee may winne the <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13712:29"/>loue and hearrs of his ſubiects, the meaneſt whereof may be able to doe him ſome kinde of ſeruice, at one time or other. For <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth, that the onely inexpugnable force of a Prince, is the loue of his ſubiects. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> in his ſpeeches to his Councell, commending his ſonne vnto them, ſayd: It is not the aboundance of money and Treaſure, nor the multitude of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uldiers that maintayneth a Prince, and cauſeth him to be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed, but the loue of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. For thoſe (ſayth hee) doe onely long and ſarely Reigne, who doe ingraue in the hearts of their ſubiects, not a feare by force and cruelty, but a loue by bounty and liberality. And thoſe that willingly yeelde to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and are not contrayned by ſeruitude, ought not to be ſuſpected of the Prince. And ſubiects (ſayth he) neuer refuſe to obey but when they are vſed withvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and contumely. <hi>Meſiſſa</hi> King of <hi>Numidia</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting his ſonnes at his death to keepe amity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt them, ſayd: It is not the great forces, nor Armies, nor great Treaſure by which a Prince ſhould preſerue and maintayne his eſtate, but friends, who are not gorten by force of Armes, nor with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but by good vſage and loyalty.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> ſayth, that a Prince can haue no greater, better, nor fitter inſtruments to keepe and conſerue his eſtate, then good friends: Wherefore a Prince ſhould haue care alwayes of his ſubiects, and vſe them well. For <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> would ſay, that hee had rather preſerue one of his ſubiects, then kill a thouſand of his enemies. And <hi>Pribagoras</hi> affirmeth, that ſubiects are to the Prince, as the Winde to the fire, for the ſtronger the Wind is, the greater is the fire: So the richer the Subiects be, the ſtronger the Prince. But where Matcheuils principle taketh effect, there the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects muſt be made poore by continuall Subſidies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, and impoſitions, that the people may be alwayes <pb n="54" facs="tcp:13712:30"/>kept vnder as ſlaues, and feare the Prince, which courſe extinguiſheth the loue of the people towards the Prince, and ingendreth hatred. Therefore <hi>Pythagoras</hi> counſell is better: And a Prince to enrich his ſubiects, the only way is to keepe them in peace, without quarrels, and diſſentions, and too gricuous exactions. Therefore <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Commines</hi> blameth greatly ſuch Princes as doe not ſeeke to compound and end diſſentions and quarrels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their greateſt ſubiects, but rather doe nouriſh the one part, wherein they doe but ſet their owne houſe on fire, as did the Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt, taking part with the Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> againſt the Earle of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> which cauſed the Warre betwixt the Houſe of
<hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeauenth King of <hi>France,</hi> beeing Dolphin, taking part with the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> was the cauſe that the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> brought <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth into
<hi>France.</hi> And for exactions, the Emperour <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> made a Law called <hi>Auguſta,</hi> that no payment ſhould be exacted of the people, but for the profite of the Common-wealth. And when <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> layd a double taxe vppon the people, they anſwered, That if he would haue two taxes in one yeare, hee muſt giue them two Summers, two Harueſts, and two Vintages. For the people cannot endure to bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged: if they bee, great inconuenience may grow thereby. For <hi>Phillip Le Bell</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> being receiued in <hi>Flanders</hi> as Lord thereof, charged the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with exceſſiue taxes, and ſuffered the French to commit all inſolency and iniuries againſt the people, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring the Nobility, and exempting them from all taxes, impoſitions, and charges, whereupon they of <hi>Bruges</hi> begunne to reuolte, and killed all the French in the Towne. After this the <hi>Flemengs</hi> ouer-threw the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of King
<hi>Phillip,</hi> and freed themſelues from the French.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13712:30"/>
               <p>Therefore if the Princes Councell, or Nobility, doe yeelde to haue any thing impoſed vpon the people, it is fitting they ſhould not be exempt, but beginne and lay it firſt vppon themſelues as the
<hi>Romanes</hi> did, for the people murmuring againſt the Conſuls for impoſing a great charge vppon them, Conſull <hi>Leuinius</hi> ſayd: As the chiefe Magiſtrate is in honour aboue the Senate, and the Senate aboue the people, ſo ought he to be a guide, and the firſt to ſubmit himſelfe to endure all kinde of paine and trouble: For if thou wilt impoſe a charge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thy inferiour, firſt beginne and lay it vpon thy ſelfe, and the reſt will more eaſily follow: therefore let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with our ſelues, ſayd hee, and ſo they did. The great impoſitions the Prince of
<hi>Wales</hi> layd vppon the Councrey of <hi>Guienne,</hi> was a great cauſe of the loſſe thereof. The Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> Gouenour of
<hi>France</hi> for <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt, was extreamely hated of the
<hi>Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for a great impoſition he layd vpon them, for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof, the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> leuyed great forces, and in the end cauſed the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> to bee killed.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Aniou</hi> regent of <hi>France,</hi> laying a great impoſition vpon the people, a Collector thereuppon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding a Denier of a poore VVoman for a basket of Herbes, which ſhee refuſing to pay, hee forced to take her Herbes, but ſhe crying, was reſcued by the people, and an vproare did ariſe, which did great hurt before it could be appeaſed. The Earle of <hi>Flanders</hi> likewiſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great impoſition vppon the people, made them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt him. And <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth King of
<hi>France,</hi> making Warre againſt <hi>Lodowicke Sforce</hi> Duke of
<hi>Milan,</hi> who knowing himſelfe to be very edious to his ſubiects, for his great exactions and impoſitions, and fearing that they would abandon him, aſſembled the people at <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> and to gaine their good wills, remitted diuers taxes which he had impoſed vpon them, and gaue them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13712:31"/>many reaſons and excuſes for his former proceedings. But ſuch hatred they had conceiued againſt him, as all would not ſerue, for within few dayes after, they tooke armes, called in the French, killed his Treaſurer, and made him flee. When the Battell of <hi>Creſſy</hi> was fought, the people of <hi>France</hi> were in extreame pouerty, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the euill gouernment of the publicke Treaſure, of the falſe-hood of the Treaſurers and Magiſtrates (who enriched themſelues by the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerty of the people) and of the increaſe of Taxes, Subſidies and Impoſitions, which orew the people into diſpaire (oppreſſed alſo with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Plagues) that when the King would haue leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an other Army, hee could not get the French to it. A Prince therefore ſhould loue and cheriſh his Subiects, but not oppreſſe them. For <hi>Tyberius Nero,</hi> when ſome perſwaded him to take great Tributes of the Prouinces, ſayd, that a good ſhepheard ſhould ſheare his ſheepe, but not deuoure them. And <hi>Lewes</hi> the ninth King of
<hi>France,</hi> his chiefe care in ſparing was to eaſe the people by abating the Taxes and Subſidies layd vppon them by his Predeceſſors. And that State (ſayth <hi>Thales</hi>) is beſt ordered which hath it, neither too wealthy, nor too poore Citizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 25. <hi>Who to haue the charge in Warre.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOrce and Valour moſt properly ſhould belong to the Nobility, and they thereby defend the people, and bee their Leaders in Warre. Therefore for a Prince to take that charge from them, or to diſplace them, if they be ſufficient, is not conuenient. For <hi>Perennis</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the whole gouernement vnder the Emperour <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus,</hi> diſplaced all the Noble Captaines, and put o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baſe perſons in their roomes, whereat the Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grieued, pulled <hi>Perennis</hi> in peeces, as an enemy to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13712:31"/>the Common wealth. <hi>Anno</hi> enuying the glory of
<hi>Mutines<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> tooke his charge from him, and gaue it to his owne ſonne. Whereupon <hi>Mutines</hi> practiſed with the Confull and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed to him the Towne of
<hi>Agrigente</hi> in <hi>Cicily,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all <hi>Cicily</hi> was brought in ſubiection to the <hi>Romanes. Lewes</hi> the eleuenth King of
<hi>France,</hi> diſplacing the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen and his good ſeruants, and giuing the Offices to men or baſe quality; ciuill Warre did ariſe, but the King preſently acknowledging his errour, reſtored them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Yet it behoueth a Prince to be reſpectiue, and not to giue a charge to a ſeuere man. For ſometimes a good Prince ſhall be hated for his wicked Gouernour, as was
<hi>Scipio,</hi> for the cruelty of his Lieutenant <hi>Pleninius.</hi> And
<hi>Lucullus,</hi> though he was wiſe and Valiant, and did many exploits againſt <hi>Mythridates,</hi> and <hi>Tygranes,</hi> two of the greateſt Kings of <hi>Aſia,</hi> yet was hee ſo ſeuere and vncourteous, as his ſouldiers loued him not, neyther would obay him in the end. Whereupon the
<hi>Romanes</hi> ſet <hi>Pompey</hi> in his place, who by his courteſie and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency wonne the hearts of his ſouldiers, and thereby brought all the Eaſt parts vnder the obedience of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> and ſo reaped the fruites of <hi>Lucullus</hi> labours, and had the honour thereof with Tryumph.
<hi>Appius Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> vſed in like manner great rigour and ſeuerity amongſt his ſouldiers, inſomuch as they would doe nothing for him, though he put ſome of the Captaines to death, but reioyced to be ouer-throwne, to diſhonour him. And at another time the <hi>Romane</hi> ſouldiers, for deſpite they had againſt the Ten-men, ſuffered themſelues to be vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. And <hi>Marcus Popilius</hi> Confull ſubduing the
<hi>Lygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> (now <hi>Geneuois</hi>) rebelling againſt the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Towne walls, tooke their armour from them; and ſold them, and their goods: which the Senate thought to be a too ſeuere and cruell part of <hi>Popilius,</hi> and an euill example for others to ſtand vppon extreamity, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to yeeld, or to truſt to the clemency of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</hi> 
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:13712:32"/>Therefore commaunded all that were ſold to bee redeemed, their goods to be reſtored, they ſuffered to haue armour, and <hi>Popilius</hi> to bee called home, and his gouernement giuen to another. Therefore a Prince for his Warres had neede to appoynt not onely a wiſe, but a temperate and Valiant Commander. For (<hi>Plato</hi> ſayth) that a man temperate not endued with fortitude, falleth eaſily into cowardlineſſe, and baſeneſſe of minde; and that a ſtrong and Valiant man without remperance, is eaſily carried away with temerity and boldneſſe. So was <hi>Flaminius</hi> ouer-throwne and killed by
<hi>Hanniball</hi> at <hi>Traſamene,</hi> for not ſtaying to ioyne his forces with the other Conſull. And <hi>Minutius</hi> in the abſence of
<hi>Fabius,</hi> hauing charge and commaund ouer the Army, vppon his raſh attempt againſt <hi>Hanniball,</hi> had good ſucceſſe. Whereupon he would needes haue the Army diuided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, and haue equall charge: to which <hi>Fabius</hi> condiſcended: <hi>Hauniball</hi> perceiuing his raſhneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence, gaue him battell and ouer-threw him; but
<hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> being at hand, gaue him ſuccours, whereuppon
<hi>Minutius</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed his errour. And then <hi>Hanniball</hi> ſaid, that the Cloud which had wont to hang vpon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, ſturred with Wind and Temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, was ruined to Raine; for <hi>Fabius</hi> kept the heights and would not fight but with good aduantage; therefore <hi>Hanniball</hi> feared his wiſedome.</p>
               <p>And when <hi>Fabius</hi> had gotten the Towne of <hi>Tarent</hi> by Treaſon, <hi>Hanuiball</hi> ſayd, I perceiue the <hi>Romanes</hi> haue alſo their <hi>Hanniball.</hi> But at <hi>Treue, Hanuiball</hi> defeated the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> who came to battell faſting, which was a great ouer-fight in the Confull. But <hi>Hanniball</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded all his men to eate ſome meate before. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus,</hi> through the default of his owne ſouldiers, was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne by <hi>Hanuiball;</hi> but his wiſedome was ſuch, as firſt rebuking his ſouldiers therefore, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of them, he gaue battell the next day to <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball,</hi> 
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13712:32"/>and deſeated him. But the Confull <hi>Minutius</hi> was of a weaker ſpirit, temperate without fortitude, for hee being ſent agaynſt the <hi>Eques,</hi> durſt not come neere them, but fortified himſelfe in his Campe, which they ſeeing, beſieged him in his Tents. Whereupon <hi>Lucius Quintiut</hi> was created Dictator, who relieued him, and ſubdued the <hi>Eques,</hi> but would giue no part of the ſpoyle, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Minutius,</hi> nor to his ſouldiers, but rebuked them. So that Wiſedome, Temperance, and Valour, are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in a Generall.</p>
               <p>Diſſention likewiſe in an Army is to be auoyded, for by the diffention betwixt the Conſuls, <hi>Hanniball</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw them at the battell of <hi>Cannas</hi> Therefore <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Neron,</hi> and <hi>M. Lucins</hi> being enemies, and choſen Conſuls, made themſelues friends, for the good of the Common-wealth. So <hi>Ariſtides</hi> and
<hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> ſent Embaſſadours by <hi>Athens,</hi> did reconcile themſelues du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that imployment. <hi>Cretes</hi> and
<hi>Hermias</hi> not friends, and being in their Citty of <hi>Magnetia</hi> beſieged by <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates, Cretes</hi> offered <hi>Hermias</hi> the charge of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Generall, and to depart the Citty himſelfe: or if
<hi>Hermias</hi> had rather depart, then to leaue that Office to him, leaſt by their both being in Towne, iealouſie might grow betwixt them, and breed hurt to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. <hi>Hermias</hi> ſeeing the honeſt offer of his Companion, and knowing him to be the more ſufficient, yeelded to him the charge, and left the Towne.</p>
               <p>And as diſſention is hurtfull, ſo enuy is not fitting. For the French men ayding <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> agaynſt
<hi>Denis</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> had vpon their earneſt requeſt, the poynt of the battell, which did offend the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, who were deſirous thereof, inſomuch that the French-men giuing the charge, the Spaniard would not ſecond them, but ſuffered them all to be ſlayne or taken, and then they ſet vpon the <hi>Portugals,</hi> who hauing van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the French, and ſeeing the <hi>Castilians</hi> come, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all their priſoners, and then ouer-threw them alſo: <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13712:33"/>Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth, and the French King, ſent great forces agaynſt the Turke
<hi>Bajazet:</hi> Their Generall was the Earle of <hi>Neuers,</hi> who againſt the will of the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and of all the Campe gaue the firſt charge, and without order, and was ouer-throwne, whereupon the Army of the Chriſtians fled. <hi>Anno</hi> 1396. by reaſon whereof the Turk tooke al <hi>Greece,</hi> and the greateſt part of <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> and then beſieged <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it is alſo very requiſite that the Generall ſhould keep his ſouldiers from idleneſſe, for <hi>Segnities robur fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, longa otianeruos.</hi> Sloath weakneth the ſinewes, and diminiſheth a mans force, and is the nurſe of all vice, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a man moſt baſe. Therefore
<hi>Aeleas</hi> a King of <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia</hi> ſayd, that hee thought himſelfe no better then his Horſe-keeper, when hee was idle. A vice to which Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen alwayes haue beene too much giuen. Inſomuch that in
<hi>Athens</hi> (where they did not ſuffer the people to be idle: a Citizen being iudicially condemned for idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, one <hi>Herondas</hi> requeſted one to ſhew him the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that was condemned for a Gentle-mans life. In <hi>Carthage,</hi> to auoyde this vice, the Noble-men did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes exerciſe Armes; the common people laboured; and the Learned men were euer teaching and inſtructing others. And in the Common-wealth of the
<hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> none were idle, for all men laboured; and they ſending one <hi>Chilon</hi> to <hi>Corinthe,</hi> to treate of a League, hee found the Magiſtrates idlely exerciſed, playing at Dice: whereuppon hee returned home, and would not ſpeake of his Commiſſion, ſaying: That hee would not ſtayne the glory of <hi>Sparta</hi> with ſo great an ignominy, as to ioyne them in ſociety with ſuch kinde of people. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> cauſed his ſouldiers to make Trenches when there was no cauſe, onely to keepe them from idleneſſe. <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> hauing an aſſured peace, for the avoyding of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, kept thirty thouſand men, twelue yeares in working the Channell <hi>Fucinus,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> might haue good water. And when the Lawes were well kept in <hi>Rome,</hi> at the time
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13712:33"/>they had Warres with the <hi>Celtiberians</hi> in
<hi>Spaine,</hi> and with <hi>Alexander;</hi> the Senators went three dayes about <hi>Rome</hi> with the Cenſors, and could not find one idle man for a meſſenger to carry their letters. But in <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius</hi> time there were plenty, for he confeſſeth that hee baniſhed, puniſhed, and put to death in his time 30000. idle Vagabonds, and 10000. idle women. And
<hi>France</hi> being troubled with a great number of idle vagabond ſouldiers: <hi>Bertrand de Gueſclin,</hi> (to free the Countrey of them) drew them all to goe with him into <hi>Spaine</hi> agaynſt the <hi>Sarazins. Bruce</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> exhorted his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to exerciſe Armes alwayes, for that idleneſſe would corrupt them, and for want of practiſe they would not be able to reſiſt their enemies. A Prince therefore being the Lanterne to his ſubiects, ſhould giue good example herein. <hi>Alfred</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> had that care to eſchew idleneſſe, and to ſpend his time well, as he diuided the day into three parts, by a Taper that burned continually in his Chappel 24. houres: The firſt part he ſpent in Prayer and in ſtudy: The ſecond part hee employed in the affaires of the Common-wealth; and the third part he tooke for his recreation and reſt. A good preſident for other Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 26. <hi>A Prince to be well aduiſed before hee begin Warre, and carefull in his fight.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not for a Prince vpon euery quarrell to make War, but to be ſure that the cauſe bee good and iuſt, which then wil bring honor to his Perſon, ſafety to his ſoule, and great encouragement to all his ſouldiers. Yet (according to the ſaying of <hi>Octauius Caeſar</hi>) neyther battell, nor War is to be vndertaken, vnleſſe there may be euidently ſeene more hope of gayne, then feare of damage: for ſuch as ſought after the ſmalleſt commodities not with a little danger, he likened vnto thoſe that Angle with a golden hooke, for the loſſe whereof, if it hapned to be ſuapped or broken off, no draught of Fiſh whatſoeuer was able to <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13712:34"/>make amends. And it is neceſſary that a Prince, or his Generall, ſhould conſult and take counſell before hee fight, for the aduice of his Captaynes heerein may doe great good. Therefore the <hi>Carthagintans</hi> commaunded thoſe Captaynes to be hanged, that got Victory without any conſultation before. And thoſe that did firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and then were ouer-throwne, they did neuer puniſh. And hauing taken counſell and reſolution, execution is to follow without delay, leaſt occaſion be loſt. For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> ſayth, that a wiſe man ought to counſell ſlowly, and execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſpeedily; and if Victory be gotten, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it hotly is the beſt, before the enemy (being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged) be able to make head agayne. For if <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> had done ſo after the battell of
<hi>Cannas,</hi> and not lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred to refreſh his men, he had taken
<hi>Rome.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Pompey</hi> in a skirmiſh, put
<hi>Caeſar</hi> to the worſe, which if he had purſued, he had quite ouer-throwne <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Yet a man muſt take heed he follow not the Victory too fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor out of order. For ſo <hi>Phillip</hi> King of
<hi>Macedonta,</hi> by following the <hi>Romanes</hi> too fiercely was defeated. So likewiſe <hi>Gaston de Foix,</hi> hauing wonne the battell at
<hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna,</hi> purſuing too fiercely a ſquadron of Spaniards that fled, by them was ouer-throwne, loſt his life, and made all that a prey to the enemy, which before hee had Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered in <hi>Italy.</hi> And an enemy is not to be contemned, though his Forces be inferiour, for oftentimes it is not the multitude of men that getteth the Victory, but the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and reſolute mindes of the fouldiers, aſſiſted by God. For King <hi>Alexander</hi> with 33000. foote-men, and 25000. horſe-men, ouer-threw the
<hi>Perſians:</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> army of 400000. foot-men, and 100000. horſe-men. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert le Friſon,</hi> with a few, and without experience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Frances</hi> great Army and old Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. The Earle of <hi>Namure</hi> with the Flemings being but a few, ouer-thre the Earle of <hi>Artois,</hi> ſent by <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the fayre King of <hi>France,</hi> with 40000. French-men into <hi>Flanders,</hi> whereof
300. efcaped not. At the battell of <pb n="63" facs="tcp:13712:34"/>
                  <hi>Peitiers</hi> the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> with 8000. Engliſh, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw 40000. French, tooke King <hi>Iohn</hi> and his Sonne priſoners, and alſo a number of Princes and Noble-men. <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth at the battell of <hi>Agincourt</hi> with 7000 o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-threw 80000. French. <hi>Simon</hi> Earle of <hi>Monford</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged in the Caſtle of <hi>Mirebeau</hi> in <hi>France</hi> by the King of <hi>Arragon</hi> and others and hauing with him but 2. Knights, 60. horſe-men, and 700. foot-men, hauing commended themſelues to God, ſallied and charged the King ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, that he ouerthrew his Army, killed him and 17000. of his men, and loſt not aboue eight foot-men of all his. Therefore a Prince ſhould not preſume too much of his owne ſtrength, nor be careleſſe of his enemy, nor charge him but in good order. For, fighting without order, the <hi>Carpentines, Olcades,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aceos</hi> in
<hi>Spaine,</hi> hauing an Army of 100000. were ouer-throwne by
<hi>Hanniball,</hi> for they truſted in the number of their Souldiers, and kept no order. Both the <hi>Scipioes</hi> being ſlayne in <hi>Spaine, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Martius</hi> being a man of meane calling, yet a good Souldier and of great courage, gathered the diſperſed ſouldiers together, and was choſen for their Generall. <hi>Aſdrubals</hi> making no account of him, ſet vppon him d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orderly, and was ouer-throwne, by which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> encouraged <hi>Martius</hi> in the night following to ſet vpon <hi>Aſdrubals</hi> Campe vppon a ſuddayne, and killed of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> 37000. and tooke priſoners 1830. And the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Romanes</hi> wearied with the ſeruice vppon the Sea, were perſwaded that they would fight no more by Sea, and therefore grew very careleſſe, whereby they were ouer-throwne by the Conſull <hi>Catulus.</hi> And the <hi>Romanes</hi> held it not ſo good to defend, as to inuade. For they hauing firſt Warre with the <hi>Carthag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nians</hi> in <hi>Cicily,</hi> thought it better to fight agaynſt them in their owne Country, then in
<hi>Cicily.</hi> Therefore ſent the Conful with forces into <hi>Affrick,</hi> which forced the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> after 14. yeares war to ſeeke for Peace, and to leaue to the <hi>Romans</hi> al <hi>Cicily,</hi> and the Ilands
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13712:35"/>betwixt it and <hi>Italy,</hi> and to giue them 2200. Talents of ſiluer, and all their priſoners without ranſome. In the ſecond War <hi>Punicke</hi> the <hi>Romanes</hi> hauing loſt many bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, ſpent their men, and conſumed their Treaſure, <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> being choſen Conſull, deſired notwithſtanding to go with an Army into
<hi>Affricke,</hi> holding that the beſt courſe to end the Warre in
<hi>Italy.</hi> But <hi>Fabius</hi> miſliked thereof, as did alſo the moſt of the Senate, wiſhing him to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <hi>Hanniball,</hi> and to driue him out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſo to quiet his owne Country, before hee inuaded an other, alleadging alſo that they were not able to maintayne two ſo great Armies, as one in <hi>Affricke;</hi> and another in <hi>Italy</hi> againſt <hi>Hanniball,</hi> who if he ſhould beſiege <hi>Rome, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> could not ſo eaſily be called from <hi>Affricke,</hi> as
<hi>Fabius</hi> was from <hi>Capua,</hi> to ſuccour <hi>Rome.</hi> They alleadged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Death of his Father and Vocle in <hi>Spaine,</hi> after their many great Victories, and the ouer-throw of <hi>Athens,</hi> by ſending a yong man to inuade <hi>Cicily:</hi> The vncertainty of the fauour of
<hi>Syphax</hi> and <hi>Maſiniſſa,</hi> and the certainty of all thoſe Countries to be their enemies. To which <hi>Scipio</hi> anſwered, that he was Conſull, not to continue Warre, but to make an end of Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> greater courage a man doth aſſault his enemy, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fend his owne, and that <hi>Agathocles</hi> King of <hi>Syracuſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſeeing <hi>Cicily</hi> troubled with Warre, turned it into <hi>Affricke</hi> from whence it came; and that a Captaine ought to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his good fortune and occaſion; and that ſtrangers ſhould well know wee haue courage as well to inuade <hi>Affricke,</hi> as to defend <hi>Italy;</hi> and that there is a
<hi>Romane</hi> Captayne dare vndertake as much as <hi>Hanniball,</hi> and will force him to returne to defend <hi>Carthage.</hi> In the end, after long arguing of the matter, it was granted that <hi>Scipio</hi> ſhould paſſe into <hi>Affricke:</hi> which hee did, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Hanniball</hi> (after hee had continued Warre in <hi>Italy</hi> ſixteene yeares) to returne home, then ouer-threw him, and made <hi>Carthage</hi> glad to accept of any conditions of peace. Which was, that <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould liue in liberty, and <pb n="65" facs="tcp:13712:35"/>vſe their Lawes, and poſſeſſe the Townes and Countryes they had before the Warres; and that they ſhould yeeld all Rebels, Fugitiues, and Priſoners, and all their Gallies ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ten, and all their Elephants tamed, and ſhould tame no more; that they ſhould not make Warre, neyther with <hi>Affricke</hi> nor without, but by permiſſion of the <hi>Romans;</hi> and that they ſhould deliuer 100. Oſtages, the yongeſt not vnder 14. yeares of age, nor the eldeſt aboue ſixty yeares, with diuers other conditions. The Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thoſe of <hi>Cyrtha,</hi> that if they would haue peace at home, they ſhould make continuall Watres abroad. But a good peace is alwayes to be embraced by a Prince, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be offered to his enemy. For as the Frenchman ſaith, <hi>La roue de la fortune, n'eſt pas touſours vne.</hi> The wheele of Fortune is not alwayes one. In the firſt War Punike <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius Claudius</hi> offered the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> peace, in reſpect of the alliance betwixt the <hi>Romanes</hi> and them, which they refuſed; but after, they fearing the <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſent to the Conſull
<hi>Attilius</hi> for peace, who denyed them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe they had refuſed it before of <hi>Claudius:</hi> which made them deſperate, and cauſed ſo long and grieuous Warre. And after the Battell of <hi>Cannas, Hanniball</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Carthage</hi> for more ayde: <hi>Hannon</hi> a graue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour, would haue had them to haue made peace with the
<hi>Romanes,</hi> whoſe counſell they refuſed, which brought ruine vpon themſelues. Yet <hi>Scipio</hi> (after hee had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne <hi>Syphax</hi> and <hi>Aſdruball</hi>) being ſent to by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> for a peace, denyed them not, but ſayd, though he had the Victory almoſt in his hands, yet would hee not refuſe to treate of peace; that all Nations may vnderſtand that the <hi>Romanes</hi> do both begin, and finiſh their Warre moſt iuſtly, and the reupon ſet them downe conditions of peace, which they ſeemed to like in retaining the time only til <hi>Hannibals</hi> comming home, who was ſent for: and vpon his arriuall, he himſelfe moued
<hi>Scipio</hi> to peace, who told <hi>Hanibal,</hi> that <hi>Carthage</hi> had but diſſembled with him, till his returne, and broken the truce. Therefore he demanded <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13712:36"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13712:45"/>amends, beſides the conditions firſt offered, which if he thought too hard, then to prepare himſelfe to Battell. The next day <hi>Scipio</hi> ouer-threw <hi>Hanniball,</hi> killed 20000. and tooke as many priſoners. Then <hi>Hanniball</hi> confeſſed himſelfe to be vanquiſhed, and told
<hi>Carthage,</hi> they had no way but accept of any conditions of Peace.
<hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> ſeeking to the <hi>Romanes</hi> for peace, had conditions offered, which he refuſed; and was ouer-throwne, then glad to accept of any conditions.</p>
               <p>The Common-wealth of <hi>Tyrus</hi> ſent to <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> offering him what obedience and ſubiection hee would require of them, ſo neyther hee nor his men would enter their Citty: <hi>Alexander</hi> refuſed it, diſdayning that one City ſhould ſhut their Gates agaynſt him, to whom the whole world was open; but after foure months ſiege, bee would haue accepted of that offer, and they then would not, being growne bold and proud. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Alexander</hi> with a furious aſſault tooke the Towne, ſpoyled it, and put all the Inhabitants to the ſword, or to bee ſlaues. But King <hi>Clotaire</hi> of <hi>France</hi> refuſing the ſubmiſſion of the <hi>Turingians,</hi> who had rebelled agaynſt him, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e them deſperate, and by deſperate fight they ouer-threw the King, who hardly eſcaped. The Earle of
<hi>Flanders</hi> likewiſe refuſing the ſubmiſſion of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, was by them ouer-throwne, and in the end they ſubmitted themſelues to
<hi>Edward</hi> the third, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> By this it doth appeare what hurt may grow by not giuing peace demaunded, and not accepting of peace offered. Therefore <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> of <hi>Sabine,</hi> becauſe the
<hi>Sabines</hi> would not yeeld to Peace, did forſake his Countrey, and went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was made a Cittizen of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:13712:36"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13712:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:13712:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13712:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:13712:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:13712:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:13712:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13712:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13712:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:13712:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13712:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:13712:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13712:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:13712:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:13712:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:13712:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13712:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
